<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<birds>
	<bird>
		<Name>Indian Peafowl</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia </Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata </Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Galliformes</Order>
		<Family>Phasianidae</Family>
		<Genus>Pavo</Genus>
		<Species>P. cristatus </Species>
		<Zoological_name>Pavo cristatus</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Sariska Tiger Reserve, Kanha National Park and Ranthambore National Park </Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Males are about 107 cm long and females are about 86 cm long. Males weigh around 5 kg and the females weigh around 3.4 kg. Both have fan shaped crest on their head. Three toes face forward and one backward. The most attracting part of the peacock is the fan or train of feathers that grow from its shimmering blue back. The train is approximately 1.6 m in length. It can also raise its train of feathers. The peahens do not have train, her plumage is brown, white and black in colour. They have royal blue neck and breast. Indian Peafowl is one of the most colorful bird. It is the largest member of pheasant and turkey family</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Peafowls are found all over India. In Haryana they are found in almost every village. They can be spotted in Sariska Tiger reserve, Kanha National Park and Ranthambore National Park. It is the National Bird of India</Presence>
		<Habitat>Peafowls prefers semi- desert grasslands, shrub, cultivated fields, open forests, orchards and deciduous forests</Habitat>
		<Diet>Peafowls are omnivorous and feed on the ground. They eat seeds, grains, insects, berries, plants, fruits, reptiles, arthropods and amphibians. They mostly search for food in early morning hours or before the sunset</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Males attract the females with the fan dance. They lay 4- 8 eggs which are hatched within 28 days. The eggs are light brown in colour. The young ones are known as peachicks. Breading season varies geographically. Males usually mates with 2- 5 females</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Not endangered. They are protected throughout the country, especially under Indian wildlife protection Act 1972. Indian Peafowls are also kept as a pet. It is considered as sacred among the Hindus</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>The average lifespan of the Indian Peafowls is about 20 years of age</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Indian Roller</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia </Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata </Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Coraciiformes</Order>
		<Family>Coraciidae</Family>
		<Genus>Coracias</Genus>
		<Species>C. benghalensis</Species>
		<Zoological_name>C. benghalensis</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Corbett National Park, Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary, Rajaji National Park, Muthanga Wildlife Sanctuary, Nagarhole National Park and Kanha National Park in India. </Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Indian Roller is also called Blue Jay. It is 13 inch long and is striking blue in colour. Indian Roller weighs around 80 -100 g. It's eyes and bill are black. It has a large head and short neck. Its crown, lower wings and tail are blue green in colour. The throat and upper breast are purple in colour. The back and abdomen are gray in colour. Males and females are similar in appearance</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Indian Roller is found in the foot hills of the Himalayas, Southern India and Western India. It can also be spotted in the Corbett National Park, Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary, Rajaji National Park, Muthanga Wildlife Sanctuary, Nagarhole National Park and Kanha National Park in India</Presence>
		<Species>The other two species of Indian Roller include European Roller (Coracias garrulus), and Dollarbird (Eurystomus orientalis) </Species>
		<Habitat>Indian Roller prefers open ground, cultivated fields, local parks and cities at lower elevation</Habitat>
		<Diet>Indian Roller is omnivorous. It mainly feeds on frogs. It also favours lizards, acorns, grasshoppers, crickets, Butterflies and moths</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Incubation takes 18 – 20 days. It lays 4- 5 eggs in the month of March or April. . Males perform ornate sexual displays during the mating season. The eggs are white in colour. It lay eggs in hole in the trees. The Young are fledged between 17 -20 days. Both the males and females take care of the young ones</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Indian Roller is considered as sacred among the Hindus. It has been given the status of State Bird of Karnataka in India. They are sometimes haunted for sports and food</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>The longevity of Indian Roller exceeds up to 17 years of age</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Great Indian Bustard</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia </Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Gruiformes</Order>
		<Family>Otididae</Family>
		<Genus>Ardeotis</Genus>
		<Species>A. nigriceps </Species>
		<Zoological_name>Ardeotis nigriceps </Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary (Gurgaon), Desert National Park (Rajasthan) and the Lala-Parjau sanctuary in western Kutch (Gujarat)</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Males are 120 cm long and weigh around 18 kg. Females are generally 92 cm longand weigh around 6 kg. Males weigh around three times more than the females. Its underparts and neck is white in colour, it has a black clown on its forehead and and its upperparts are brown in colour. Males have larger crown as compared to the females. It is tall long legged bird. Its wings are black, brown and gray in colour. Both males and females are similar in appearance</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Great Indian Bustard is mostly found in the Gujrat, Madhya Pradesh, Jammu and Kashmir, Karnataka, Andhra Pradesh and West Rajasthan. It is mainly spotted in the the Desert National Park (Rajasthan) and the Lala-Parjau sanctuary in western Kutch (Gujarat).</Presence>
		<Habitat>Great Indian Bustard prefers short grass plains, desert plains and semi arid regions</Habitat>
		<Diet>Great Indian Bustard is omnivorous and feeds on beetles, grasshoppers, seeds and groundnuts</Diet>
		<Reproduction>It makes nest in the open ground, where incubated by female for about 25 days; fledging period 30–35 days. It usually lay single egg in an year. First breeding occurs at 5–6 years in males and 2–3 years in females. Males take no part in nourishing the young ones</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Great Indian Bustard has been declared as the endangered species, as its population is very less in number. Due to haunting and greater use of pesticides, the population of Great Indian Bustard is continuously declining. As these birds do not live in birds, so there is greater risk of their eggs destruction. The largest protected area of the Great Indian Bustard is the Desert National Park in India</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>Unknown</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Lammergeier</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Falconiformes</Order>
		<Family>Accipitridae</Family>
		<Genus>Gypaetus</Genus>
		<Zoological_name>Gypaetus barbatus </Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Dachigam National Park , Ranthambore National Park, Valley of Flowers, Khangchendzonga National Park in India</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Lammergeier are also called Bearded Vulture. It is 108 cm long and weighs around 5- 7 kg. Its wings are three meter long. They do-not have a bald head. Its tail and wings are gray in colour. They have gray blackish hair on their back, wings and tail. They have long, pointed wings and wedged tail. Its eyes are covered with the dark feathers. Its chest is reddish brown in colour. It has spots on the breast and have black and white stripes on the head. Its underparts are pale brown in colour</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>It is wide spread in the Indian Himalayas. Dachigam National Park , Ranthambore National Park, Valley of Flowers, Khangchendzonga National Park in India</Presence>
		<Habitat>Lammergeier prefers high mountainous regions, cliffs and gorges, it lives up to an altitude of 25, 500 feet</Habitat>
		<Diet>It mainly feeds on dead animals, small mammals, small birds, turtles and carrion. It is the only bone eating bird in the world</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Lammergeier attains sexual maturity at 5 years of age. They breed from January to July. Incubation takes 53 days. Mostly one or two eggs are laid, which are hatched in 58 days. Both males and females take care of the young ones. It breeds on hollow or crags in high mountainous areas. Young ones take 107 to 117 days to fly</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Least concern. This species now survives in only few areas. Lammergeier are mostly poisoned by the humans. Poaching, destruction of natural habitat and lack of food has seriously affected the population of Lammergeier. Many countries have already started the operation of breeding this species</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>Lammergeier can live up to 40 years of age</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>White Rumped Shama</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Passeriformes</Order>
		<Family>Muscicapidae</Family>
		<Species>C. malabaricus</Species>
		<Zoological_name>Copsychus malabaricus</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Corbett National Park, Royal Chitwan National Park, Sundarbans National Park and Bandhavgarh National Park in India</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>White Rumped Shama is a famous song bird. It is medium in size. It is approximately 27 cm long and weighs around 32 grams. It has a round head, long legs and slender bills. The male is shiny dark in colour. Its head, neck and back are black bullish in colour, wings are dull black in colour, legs are pink in colour and the belly is pale orange in colour. It has along tail and broad wings. They have white feathers on the rump. Females are smaller than the males. Females are brown grayish in colour, with the white coloured belly. They have black bills</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>White Rumped Shama is found in almost all the parts of India but are they are mostly found in Northern India. It is also spotted in the Corbett National Park, Royal Chitwan National Park, Sunderbans National Park and Bandhavgarh National Park in India</Presence>
		<Habitat>White Rumped Shama prefers dense jungles and lowlands up to 1500 m</Habitat>
		<Diet>White Rumped Shama is a insectivore. It mainly feeds on insects like grasshoppers, termites and caterpillars. They also favour small intvertebrates, maggots, berries and fruits</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Incubation lasts for 12 –15 days. Males are generally aggressive during the breeding season. One egg is laid per day. The egg is white in colour with the reddish brown spots. Both males and females take care of the young ones. Young ones are born blind and featherless. They open their eyes in six days. Their feathers are completely developed in eleven days. They start flying in 14 days. They are sexually mature in 3- 4 months. Their nests are cup shaped, made of mud and leaves. Young ones feed on insects and earthworms</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Least concern. White Rumped Shama is present in large numbers</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>White Rumped Shama generally lives for 10- 15 years</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Sarus Crane</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia </Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Gruiformes</Order>
		<Family>Gruidae</Family>
		<Genus>Grus</Genus>
		<Species>G. antigone </Species>
		<Zoological_name>Grus antigone</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary, Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary, Madhav National Park, Kerala Bustard Sanctuary and Bhindawas Bird Sanctuary</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Sarus Crane reaches to the height of 200 cm with the wingspan of eight feet and weigh around 7.3 kg. This bird stands as tall as the man. It has long red legs. It's head and upper neck are also red in colour. It is highlighted with the white crown, which is covered with the green skin. It has a dark long pointed bill. Black hair like bristles cover the upper throat and neck. They have gray feathers over the ears. Females are shorter than the males. It is the world's tallest flying bird</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Sarus Crane is found in the northern, central and north-eastern pars of India. Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary, Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary, Madhav National Park, Kerala Bustard Sanctuary and Bhindawas Bird Sanctuary</Presence>
		<subspecies>There are three subspecies of Sarus Crane namely Grus antigone antigone, Grus antigone sharpii and Grus antigone gilli</subspecies>
		<Habitat>Sarus Crane prefers wetlands, cultivated fields to live</Habitat>
		<Diet>Sarus Crane is omnivorous. It feeds on he diet includes frogs, reptiles, eggs of birds, turtles eggs, invertebrates, butterflies, grasshoppers, tubers of aquatic plants, cereals, potatoes, peas, berries and seeds</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Sarus Crane reach the level of sexual maturity at 5-6 years of age. It usually breeds during the monsoon season. During the mating season both male and female dance around each other. Incubation takes 27 -35 days. Only two eggs are laid at a time. Nests are made (on the ground) in the fields near the ponds or canals. Both male and females take care of the nests. Chicks fledging takes 55 -65 days. It is the only resident breeding crane in India</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Sarus Crane is regarded as the threatened species. It is currently listed in the Schedule IV of the Wildlife (Protection) Act, 1972. IUCN (Red List) classifies Sarus Crane as vulnerable. The total population of Sarus Crane approximately lies between 13,500 to 15,500. Loss of wetland areas, egg damage by the humans and heavy use of pesticides has seriously declined the population of Sarus Crane. It is widely haunted by the villagers and is also used for the trade purpose in many countries. </Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>Longevity of Sarus Crane exceeds up to 15- 20 years in the wild and for 40 years in captivity</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Grey Heron</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata </Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Ciconiiformes</Order>
		<Family>Ardeidae</Family>
		<Genus>Ardea</Genus>
		<Species>A. cinerea </Species>
		<Zoological_name>Ardea cinerea </Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Sunderban National Park, Periyar National Park and Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary in India</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Grey Heron is 90 -100 cm long and weigh around 1- 2 kg. It size of its wingspan is 2 m. They have long neck and powerful yellow bills.It has slender S- shaped neck, narrow head and pointed dagger bill. The back and wings are gray in colour, while the underparts are white in colour. They have white head with a wispy crest of long black feathers. They have long brown legs</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Grey Heron is mostly found in the State of Haryana in India. Grey Heron can also be spotted in the Sunderbans National Park, Periyar National Park and Bharartpur Bird Sanctuary in India. It is also known as Kabud, Anjan and Nari</Presence>
		<subspecies>There are four other subspecies of Grey Heron namely Ardea cinerea cinerea Linnaeus (Europe, Africa and Westen Asia, Ardea cinerea jouyi Clark (Eastern Asia), Ardea cinerea firasa Hartert (Madagasagar), Ardea cinerea monicae Jouanin &amp; Roux (Mauritania)</subspecies>
		<Habitat>Grey Heron prefers wetland marshes, gravel pits, reservoirs, lakes, rivers and estuaries</Habitat>
		<Diet>Grey Heron feeds on fish, amphibians, arthropods(insect, spiders), crustacea (crabs), small mammals (rodents), reptiles (hatchling turtles), and small birds</Diet>
		<Reproduction>rey Heron make nests in colonies and wetlands. Their nests are 45 cm wide. Males help the females in building up the nests. Females usually lay 3- 6 eggs, which are blue green in colour. Incubation takes 24- 27 days. The young fledge in seven weeks to three months. Both the males and females take care of the young ones</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Least concern. Cold weather, habitat destruction and starvation are the main reason for the decline in population of Grey Heron. They are sometimes haunted for food</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>The longevity of the Grey Heron exceeds up to the 25 years of age</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Brown Long Eared Bat</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Chiroptera</Order>
		<Family>Vespertilionidae</Family>
		<Genus>Plecotus</Genus>
		<Species>P.auritus</Species>
		<Zoological_name>Plecotus auritus</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary and Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary in India</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Brown long eared Bat is a medium size Bat with the pink brown face.. It is 4.2- 5.3 cm long and weigh up to 5 – 12 grams. Their fur is buff brown in colour. They have long and woolly fur. The females are slightly larger and heavier than the males. The ears and wing membrane are a light gray brown. They have strikingly large oval shaped ears that are almost as long as the body. At rest, their ears are tucked back and folded, resembling ram horns. Their ears are as longer as the body and exceeds to 28 mm. It has broad wings measuring 24 -28 cm. Females are larger and heavier than the males</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Brown long eared Bat is found in the Central and Western parts of India. They are spotted in many bird sanctuaries in India especially Bharatpur Wildlife Sanctuaryand Suntanpur Bird Sanctuary in India</Presence>
		<Habitat>Brown long eared Bat prefers open forests, deciduous woodland, orchards and parklands. They roosts in old buildings</Habitat>
		<Diet>Brown long eared Bat feeds on moths, beetles, flies, earwigs, caddis flies Caterpillars, spiders, twigs and leaves. They search for food during the night</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Brown long eared Bats mate during the autumn season. Females usually mates with many males. Males produce the greatest amout of sperm in the month of August and September. One young is born between mid June to July end. New born open their eyes on the 4th day of the birth and their ears become erect on the following 11th day. Yong ones are pale gray in colour. Young ones starts flying before one month and are weaned at about month and a half. They are weaned and able to fly by the end of July</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Brown long eared Bats are not considered as threatened. They are listed as vulnerable by the IUCN. They are present in large numbers</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>Average longevity of the Brown long eared Bat extends up to the 4 years of age and the maximum to the 30 years of age</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Comb Duck</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Anseriformes</Order>
		<Family>Anatidae</Family>
		<Genus>Sarkidiornis</Genus>
		<Species>S. melanotos </Species>
		<Zoological_name>Sarkidiornis melanotos</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary, Manas National Park and Corbett National Park in India</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>They are large size ducks. Males are 76 cm long and weigh around 2250 g. Females are 56 cm long and weigh around 1750 g. Males are usually larger than the females. Their head is creamy white and neck is orange -yellow in colour. They have yellow or cinnamon flanks. Both the sexes have black bills with the males showing a comb on the top. Their lower back is gray and upper-parts are blue black in colour</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Comb Duck is mainly found in the Northern parts of India especially in the state of Haryana. It can also be spotted in the Sultanpur, Manas, Batla and Corbett national parks</Presence>
		<Habitat>Comb duck prefers fresh water swamps and lakes in tropical lowlands. They live in places away from the human settlement</Habitat>
		<Diet>Comb duck feeds on grass seeds, frogs, grain, shoots, aquatic vegetation, invertebrates and small snails</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Comb Duck reach the level of sexual maturity in 1-2 years of age. They usually mate during the rainy season. They lay nests in tree cavity or on the ground. Females lays 6- 20 eggs, which are yellow white in colour. Incubation rests for 30-32 days and the fledging duration is of 10 weeks. During the mating season males becomes larger than their normal size</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Least concern. Comb Duck is not an endangered specie. Its population has been continuously declining due to haunting and deforestation</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>The lifespan of the Comb Duck is approximately 20- 30 years of age</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Kingfisher</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Coraciiformes</Order>
		<Family>Alcedinidae</Family>
		<Genus>Alcedo</Genus>
		<Species>A. atthis </Species>
		<Zoological_name>Alcedo atthis</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Corbett National Park, Bandhavgarh National Park and Sunderbans National Park in India. </Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Common Kingfisher is 17 cm in length and weigh around 30- 34 g. Their wingspan is 30 inches long. Their underparts are bright orange in colour with the white bib. Their wings are bluish green and the tail is bright blue in colour. They have blue head with the white mark on either side of it. They have short legs which are colored in orange. The wings and tails are short while the bill is long and pointed</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Common Kingfisher is mostly found in the state of Haryana in India Common Kingfisher can also be spotted in the Corbett National Park, Bandhavgarh National Park and Sundarbans National Park in India</Presence>
		<Habitat>Common Kingfisher prefers to live near streams, slow flowing rivers, ponds and lakes. </Habitat>
		<Diet>Common kingfisher feeds on aquatic insects, small fish and prawns. They mostly hunt during the morning or evening hours</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Common Kingfisher usually mate during the spring season. Males try to attract the females with the fish in their beaks. The females lay 6 – 7 eggs. Eggs are incubated for about 20 days. Fledging period rests from 23 -27 days. They do-not build nests, they place their eggs on a litter of fish bones and disgorged pellets. Both the males and females bring food for the young ones and take care of them. Young ones are somewhat blue to pale red in colour. Most of the Kingfishers are territorial</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>east concern. They are present in large numbers. They are usually found near the streams, lakes and pounds. Their population has seriously declined due to the cold weather</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>The lifespan is of 7 years</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Cuckoo</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Cuculifomes</Order>
		<Family>Cuculidae</Family>
		<Zoological_name>Eudynamys scolopacea </Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Batla National Park, Corbett National Park, Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary, Pench National Park and Barwala Bird Sanctuary.</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Cuckoo – The Koel is 39- 46 cm in length. It is a long and slim birds. It has a long tails, pointed wings and curved bills. The male is glistening black, with yellowish green bill and crimson eyes. They have short wings but long tail. The female is dark brown, with profusely spotted and barred with white. Females have green beak and red eyes. Males and females are distinct in appearance. Tail is dark gray and slightly white in colour. The crown is dark brown and the bill is pale green in colour. Females are slightly smaller than the males</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>They are mostly found in every part of India. They can also be spotted in the Batla National Park, Corbett National Park, Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary, Pench National Park and Barwala Bird Sanctuary</Presence>
		<Habitat>Cuckoo prefers tall forests, suburban areas open moorlands, desert to tropical rainforests</Habitat>
		<Diet>Cuckoos are carnivorous. They feed on fruits, insects , caterpillars, grasshoppers, lizards, small snakes and mammals. They feed in the canopy of the trees</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Its breeding season rests from September to February. It is a brood parasite. Cuckoo lay egg in the nest of the other bird. It prefers leafy trees for foraging . A single egg is laid in the host's nest and once hatched the chick forces the other eggs and hatchlings out of the nest. When the chick leaves the nest it roosts in the outer branches of a tree, parents search for food to satisfy the young ones. Young ones resembles the females, but they have dark eyes</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Least concern. Cuckoo- The Koel is present in large number in India. </Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>Unknown</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Garganey Teal</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Anseriformes</Order>
		<Family>Anatidae</Family>
		<Genus>Anas</Genus>
		<Species>A. querquedula </Species>
		<Zoological_name>Anas querquedula </Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>RanthamboreNational Park and Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary in India. </Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Garganey Teal is 35 cm long and weigh around 316- 502 g. It has a white stripe above the eye that run down to the neck. It's underparts are gray in colour. Garganey Teal have a head with the blackish brown top portion and brownish red on the rest of the head. It has a black chin. The breast and back are brown in colour. The bill is dark gray and the legs are blue- gray. It is a small dabbling duck</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>It is well distributed through out India. It can easily be spotted in the Ranthambore National Park and Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary in India</Presence>
		<Habitat>arganey Teal prefers shallow marshes and steppe lakes</Habitat>
		<Diet>Garganey feeds on aquatic plants, seeds and invertebrates</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Garganey Teal attain sexual maturity at 1-2 years of age. It lays 7- 8 eggs. Incubation period is of 25- 26 days and fledging duration is of 6 weeks. Males help the females in guarding the chicks. They make the nest on the ground. The young ones fledge at seven weeks of age</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Habitat loss, haunting and food poising has seriously declined the population of Garganey Teal</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>The average lifespan of the Garganey Teal is approximately 20- 30 years</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Grey Junglefowl</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Galliformes</Order>
		<Family>Phasianidae</Family>
		<Genus>Gallus</Genus>
		<Species>G. sonneratii</Species>
		<Zoological_name>Gallus sonneratii </Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Bandipur National Park, Sultanpur National Park, Thattekad Bird Sanctary and Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary in India</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Male is 75 cm long and the female is 38 cm long. The comb of Grey Jungle Fowl is deep red in colour. They have long neck, which is gray blackish in colour. Their feathers are gray black in colour with white stripes</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Grey Jungle Fowl is widely found in the southern and western parts of India. Grey Jungle Fowl can also be found in the Bandipur National Park, Sultanpur National Park, Thattekad Bird Sanctary and Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary</Presence>
		<Habitat>Natural habitat of Grey Jungle Fowl is forest undergrowth and bamboo thickest.</Habitat>
		<Diet>Grey Jungle Fowl feeds on mall dog kibble, seasonal pulp seed fruits like pomegranate, pumpkin and hot peppers</Diet>
		<Reproduction>The Grey Jungle Fowl reaches the level of sexual maturity at approximately two years of age. It usually breeds between the month of March -July. Eggs incubate for 21 days. The average clutch size is between 4-6. Males can breed to more than one hen per year. Males becomes very noisy during the breeding season</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Least concern</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>Unknown</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Mallard</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata</Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Anseriformes</Order>
		<Family>Antidae</Family>
		<Genus>Anas</Genus>
		<Species>A. platyrhynchos </Species>
		<Zoological_name>Anas platyrhynchos</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Madhav National Park, Panna National Park, Nameri National Park, Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary and Hemis National Park in India.</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Mallard is 15 inches long and weigh around 750- 1,000 g. The size of its wings measures around 35 inches. They have black stripe that run horizontally through the eye. Males have gray, black and yellow bill while the females have orange bill with black central patch. Males have chestnut breast , gray flanks, upper wings coverts, black under-tail coverts contrast with white tail and have white ring around its neck. Females have pale brown face, dark cap and eye line, mottled brown and tan plumage. Both male and females have orange feet</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Mallard is found in the north and central part of India. It can also be spotted in the Madhav National Park, Panna National Park, Nameri National Park, Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary and Hemis National Park in India</Presence>
		<Habitat>Mallards prefers shallow inland waterways, such as ponds, lakes, rivers, reservoirs, and marshes</Habitat>
		<Diet>Mallard are omnivorous and feeds on seeds, plants, shoots, buds, grain, acorns, aquatic invertebrates and insects. In most parts, humans provide them abundant food through out the year</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Mallard usually make nests near water sites. Mating season rests between September and March. It lay 6- 15 eggs. Mallard reach the level of sexual maturity at one year of age. Females incubates the clutch for 28- 30 days. Young birds are fledged for 42- 60 days</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Least concern. It is one of the most widespread duck. It's population is currently increasing. This duck is not the threatened specie</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>Average lifespan of Mallard is around 29 years</Lifespan>
	</bird>
	<bird>
		<Name>Red Junglefowl</Name>
		<Kingdom>Animalia</Kingdom>
		<Phylum>Chordata </Phylum>
		<Class>Aves</Class>
		<Order>Galliformes</Order>
		<Family>Phasianidae</Family>
		<Genus>Gallus</Genus>
		<Species>G. gallus</Species>
		<Zoological_name>Gallus gallus</Zoological_name>
		<Found_in>Corbett National Park, Ramnagar National Park and Kaziranga National Park in India.</Found_in>
		<Physical_appearence>Red Junglefowl is 70 cm in length. They have total number of fourteen feathers. Its tail is approximately 28 cm in length. The Its plumage is red, gold, brown, orange, dark maroon, green and gray in colour. There are two ear shaped white patches on the either side of the head. An eclipse plumage is, for male, black long feather across the middle of his back and slender red-orange plumes on the rest of his body. For a female, an eclipse plumage cannot be distinguished, but she does moult</Physical_appearence>
		<Presence>Red Junglefowl is widely found in almost all the parts of India. It can also be spotted in the Corbett National Park, Ramnagar National Park and Kaziranga National Park in India</Presence>
		<subspecies>Gallus gallus gallus (Indochina), Gallus gallus bankiva (Java), Gallus gallus jabouillei (Vietnam), Gallus gallus murghi (India), Gallus gallus spadiceus (Myanmar), Gallus gallus domesticus (domestic chicken)</subspecies>
		<Habitat>Red Junglefowl prefers thick secondary forest or wide open areas</Habitat>
		<Diet>Red Jungle fowl is an herbivore and insectivore. It feeds on corn, soybean, worms, grass, grains and insects</Diet>
		<Reproduction>Red Junglefowl mainly breeds during the summer or spring season. Males mate with the multiple females and the females mate with the multiple males. Males make calls during the breeding season to attract the females. An egg is laid each day and is creamy white in colour. In four to five weeks the chicks are fully feathered. The typical clutch has between five to seven eggs. They reach the level of sexual maturity in five five months at age. Female reach the sexual maturity little latter than the males</Reproduction>
		<Conservation_status>Classified as Least Concern (LC) on the IUCN Red List 2006</Conservation_status>
		<Lifespan>The average lifespan of the Red Junglefowl is of approximately 25 years</Lifespan>
	</bird>
</birds>