<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<national_parks>
	<national_park>
		<name>Kaziranga National Park</name>
		<place>Bokakhat (23 km), Assam in the northeast of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Rhinos, Tigers, Leopards</major_attractions>
		<area>430 sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>From mid-November to early April months</ideal_time>
		<attractions>The lush coffee and rubber plantations of the nearby Karbi Anglong, the Karbi villages, meet the Karbi people and observe their way of living. Majuli, Sibsagar, Digboi</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Bokakhat, Guwahati, Dibrugarh, Tezpur</major_accesses>
		<where>Located on the banks of the mighty Brahmaputra River in the far North East of India, Assam, Kaziranga National Park covers an area of approximately 430 sq-km. The swamps and tall thickets of elephant grass makes the Kaziranga National Park Assam the ideal habitat for the Indian One-Horned Rhinos</where>		
		<important_date>Due to limitless poaching of the one-horned Rhinos (the prehistoric survivor), the Kaziranga National Park was declared a wildlife sanctuary in 1940</important_date>
		<flora>The land of Kaziranga Wildlife Santuary is mainly covered by dense and tall elephant grass. These large distribution of elephant grass are intermixed by small swamplands left behind by the receding floodwaters of the river Brahmaputra. These beautiful swamplands have an abundant cover of water lilies, water hyacinth and lotus. The vegetation that breaks the monotony of these grasslands and swamps are large clumps of semi-evergreen forest</flora>
		<fauna>The Kaziranga Wildlife Sanctruary is home to the great one horned Indian Rhino, about 900 in number. Other major wild attractions include a large population of Indian Elephants, Indian Bison, Swamp Deer or Barasingha, Hog Deer, Sloth Bears, Tigers, Leopard Cats, Jungle Cats, Otters, Hog Badgers, Capped Langurs, Hoolock Gibbons, Wild Boar, Jackal, Wild Buffalo, Pythons, Monitor Lizards, etc.Some other animal found here are barking deer, Sambar, golden Langurs, Slow Loris, pygmy hog, capped langur and bears</fauna>
		<avifauna>Kaziranga National Park is a birding paradise. The birds found here include the Oriental Honey Buzzard, Black-Shouldered Kite, Black Kite, Brahminy Kite, Pallas's Fishing Eagle, White Tailed Eagle, Red Junglefowl, Grey-Headed Fishing Eagle, Himalayan Griffon, etc. Huge numbers of migratory birds descend on the parks lakes and swampy areas during winters, including Greylag Geese, Bar-Headed Geese, Ruddy Shelduck, Gadwall, Falcated Duck, Red-Crested Pochard and Northern Shoveller</avifauna>
		<reptiles>Rock Pythons and many more varieties of snakes, Monitor Lizards and Turtles</reptiles>
		<safari>The vast open country makes Kaziranga National Park Assam very accessible and wildlife viewing fairly enjoyable. Here one can leave in the early hours of the dawn for an elephant-back-ride. Authorised and trained Mahouts who guide visitors through the park train the Elephants. One could see wild Elephant herds roaming around or Indian Rhinos browse past visitors unknowingly. Since Kaziranga wildlife Sanctuary is easily approachable, its provides a chance to see animals in the wild at close quarters, thus making a trip to this National Park a very pleasurable experience</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Guwahati -arr; Kaziranga,Delhi - Guwahati - Kaziranga National Park - Guwahati - Bagdogra - Kalimpong - Siliguri - Kolkata - Sunderbans National Park </travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airport is situated at Guwahati, which is 217-km away from the park. The other airport is located at Jorhat, 97-km from Kaziranga</air>
		<rail>The nearest railhead is Furkating, situated 75-km away from Kaziranga National Park.</rail>
		<road>The main gate for Kaziranga Wildlife Sanctuary, at Kohora on the NH-37, consists of a handful of cafes and a small local market. ASTC and private buses stop here on their way to and from Guwahati, Tezpur and Upper Assam</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Manas National Park</name>
		<place>Assam, in the Northeastern part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Tigers, Rhinos, Elephants</major_attractions>
		<area>391sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>During the months of November to April</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Hajo, Pabitora, Bhalukpung</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Guwahari (176 km), Tezpur</major_accesses>
		<where>Manas National Park in Assam is situated on the foothills of the Himalayas and a portion of it stretches to Bhutan (the neighbouring Princely State)</where>		
		<important_date>The Assam Manas National Park was declared a sanctuary on October 01, 1928 and was designated a World Heritage site in December 1985</important_date>
		<system>The physiology of the rehabilitation park is mostly small meadows located among densely forested foothills with many rivulets, streams and natural drains flowing all around. The park is mainly watered by the river Manas, which also forms the international boundary between India and Bhutan. In the low lands, there are many smooth sandy expanses with clumps of trees growing in, and around, them</system>
		<flora>The vegetation that covers most of the park is of the mixed deciduous variety. This mixed forest is intermixed by small glades of grass where deer can be seen grazing in huge numbers. Altogether, Manas National Park Assam offers some of the most eye-pleasing natural surroundings in the country</flora>
		<fauna>The animal population of Manas National Park Assam is very diverse. Some of the more fierce or potentially aggressive creatures it holds within it's confines are Tigers, Elephants, Rhinos, Wild Buffaloes, Leopards, Clouded Leopards and the amazingly beautiful and rare Black Panthers. The park is also a haven for highly endangered species of which it houses 20. Two of the unique residents of the park are the Hispid Hare and the Pygmy Hog.Some of the other animals sighted while exploring the park are Gaurs, Swamp Deer, Capped Langurs, Golden Langurs, Assamese Macaques, Slow Loris, Hoolock Gibbons, Smooth Indian Otters, Sloth Bears, Barking Deer, Hog Deer, Sambar and Chital</fauna>
		<avifauna>Manas National Park in Assam is a favourite with many bird species, resident and migratory. Some of these are Giant Hornbills, Red Jungle Fowls, Bulbuls, Brahminy Ducks, Khaleej Pheasants, Egrets, Pelicans, Fishing Eagles, Serpent Eagles, Falcons, Scarlet Minivets, Comb Duck, Bee-Eaters, Magpie Robins, Pied Hornbills, Gray Hornbills, Mergansers, Harriers, Ospreys and Herons</avifauna>
		<safari>The ideal way to explore a majority of the Manas National Park in Assam is in a 4-wheel (Jeep) drive petrol vehicle. The Jeep ride will get you to all the corners of the Manas Park without being too noisy. Some of the animals that comes out on the banks of the river Manas can be viewed from a boat which commences its ride from Mathanguri and ends around 35km away, from where one is picked up by pre-arranged transport. The third option, which are a favourite with most visitors, are the elephant rides organised by the park authorities from Mathanguri. These take you deep in to the densest areas of the forest and often right in between some of the wildlife there, including elephants, rhinos and wild buffaloes</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Kolkata - Manas - Kaziranga </travel-circuit>
		<air>Manas National Park is 176 km from Guwahati. The nearest airport is Borjhar, which is situated, 5 km out of town, and can be reached by rickshaw, auto rickshaw or airline buses</air>
		<rail>The nearest railhead is situated at Barpeta road</rail>
		<road>Buses regularly ply from Guwahati to Barpeta Road in 4½ hrs</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Gir Wildlife Sanctuary</name>
		<place>Gir, 42 km from Junagadh, Gujarat in the western part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Asiatic Lions, Leopards, Chowsingha</major_attractions>
		<area>1412.13 sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>Can visit Gir park throughout the year, but the best time to visit the Gir Sanctuary is between the months of November and June</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Tracks to Deva Danga, Riley's, Bawal Chowk, Kankai, Chodardi, Tulsishyam and Kamleshwar dam/lake</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Sasan (1 km), Junagadh (42 km), Ahmedabad (400 km), Veraval, Somnath</major_accesses>
		<where>The Gir National Park, the home of the Asiatic lion is located among the low, undulating and excellently irrigated hills in the Junagadh district of Gujarat in India.Gir Wildlife Sanctuary in Gujarat was created to protect the last wild population of Lion outside the African regions. Since 1913 when the Lion population over here fell drastically to just 20 animals, the numbers have grown to around 300</where>		
		<climate>The park receives a good annual rainfall averaging 1000 mm. The temperatures at the park vary to extremes. In winters, the temperatures go down to as low as 6 degrees centigrade, while soaring up to a scorching 46 degrees in the summers</climate>
		<flora>The Gir National Park is a mixed deciduous forest with well spread stock of teak, flame of the forest, some Acacia and Banyan trees. A unique belt of vegetation is found along the main rivers and streams. Species like the Jamun, Karanj, Ber, Tendu, Semul, Umro, Vad, Kalam, Charal, Sirus and Amli are found here. These trees are mostly broad leaved and evergreen, giving the area a cool shelter and the moisture content</flora>
		<fauna>Gir is not just about Indians Lions, the second most commonly found predator in the Gir is Leopard. Infact, Gir national park also houses one of the largest Leopard populations in any park in India, and especially in the hotter season they can sometimes be seen at night close to the tourist lodges.Other animal residents of the Gir national park are Sambar, Chital, Nilgai, Chowsingha, Chinkara Gazelle, Wild Boar, Langur, Jackal, Panthers, Wild Cats and Hares and Hyena.</fauna>
		<avifauna>The presence of a large number of water bodies and suitable climatic conditions prevalent within the park has made it a haven for a large number of bird species. Numerous birds like Paradise Flycatchers, Black headed Cuckoo Shrike, Gray Drongo, Pied Woodpeckers, Coppersmiths, Indian Rollers, Crested Swifts, Fish Owls, Black Vultures, Shaheen Falcons, Bonelli's Eagles, Flamingo, Crested Serpent Eagles, Painted Sandgrouse, Rock Bush Quail, Gray Partridge, Painted Storks and White Necked Storks are found here</avifauna>
		<reptiles>The reptile population of the park is mainly represented by Marsh Crocodiles, Monitor Lizards, Pythons and a large variety of snakes. There is an interesting breeding farm for crocodile at Sasan, which also provides the specimens that are relocated into the water reservoirs inside Gir</reptiles>
		<safari>The best way to see the big cats is, of course, in their natural habitats, at dawn and dusk, when they are on the prowl. Wildlife viewing in the Gir’s is best done, by driving a jeep around the forest</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Rann of Kutch - - Gondal - Gir National Park - Dandeli Wildlife Sanctuary - Goa - Mumbai </travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airport from Gir is Keshod 90 km via Veraval. Visitors can easily catch daily flights from Mumbai to Keshod</air>
		<rail>The nearest rail connection is the meter gauge rail line of 395 km from Ahemdabad</rail>
		<road>Gir is situated at a distance of 400 km from Ahmedabad via Rajkot, Junagadh and Mendarda. State Transport buses are easily available from Junagadh and Veraval to Gir, between November and June</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Sultanpur National Park</name>
		<place>Sultanpur, Haryana, in north India</place>
		<major_attractions>Migratory Birds, Kingfishers, Blue Bulls</major_attractions>
		<area>359 acres</area>
		<ideal_time>During the months of December and January</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Sultanpur Lake, Museums, Library</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Gurgaon and Delhi</major_accesses>
		<where>Sultanpur National Park and Bird Sanctuary is located in Gurgaon district of Haryana, 46 km from Delhi and 15 km from Gurgaon on the Gurgaon - Farukh Nagar Road. The Sultanpur National Park is lush with lawns and trees and shrubs and masses of bougainvillea. A good pair of binoculars is a must to clearly see the wildlife from a safe distance, without disturbing them. To facilitate bird watching, there are four watch towers (machans) located at different points. In addition there is parking and facilities for toilets and drinking water. The Educational Interpretation Center has been established here to offer proper guidance to the tourist visiting the place</where>		
		<important_date>Keeping in view Sultanpur's potential, the park area covering 359 acres was declared a Bird Sanctuary in 1971 and was upgraded to the status of National Park in 1991 by the Haryana Government</important_date>
		<system>Sultanpur National Park is essentially a bird watcher's place with few trees obscuring the visitor's view of the lake. The birds here can be easily spotted wading, swimming or flying</system>
		<flora>Efforts are being made to improve the vegetation in the area by planting more trees. The vegetation of this park is tropical and dry deciduous and the flora include grasses, dhok, khair, tendu, ber, jamun, acacia, and banyan tree</flora>
		<fauna>The wildlife in the park include blackbuck, nilgai, hog deer, sambar deer, wild dog or dhole, caracal, wild cat, hedgehog, mongoose, striped hyena, Indian porcupine, rattle/honey badger, leopard, wild pig, and four horned antelope</fauna>
		<avifauna>In 250 species of birds have been recorded in the Sultanpur Bird Sanctuary. Some of them are resident, while others come from distant regions like Siberia, Europe and Afghanistan.Some of the resident birds are - Common Hoopoe, Paddyfield Pipit, Purple Sunbird, Little Cormorant, Eurasian Thick-knee, Gray Francolin, Black Francolin, Indian Roller, White-throated Kingfisher, Spot billed Duck, Painted Stork, White Ibis, Black headed Ibis, Little Egret, Great Egret, Cattle Egret, India Crested Lark, Red vented Bulbul, Rose ringed Parakeet, Red wattled Lapwing, Shikra, Eurasian collared Dove, Red collared Dove, Laughing Dove, Spotted Owlet, Rock Pigeon, Magpie Robin, Greater Coucal, Weaver Bird, Bank Mynah, Common Mynah and Green Bee Eater.Every year 90 migratory bird species arrive here in search of feeding grounds and to pass the winter. In winter the sanctuary provides a picturesque panorama of migratory birds such as birds like - Ruff, Greater Flamingo, Black winged Stilt, Common Teal, Common Greenshank, Northern Pintail, Yellow Wagtail, White Wagtail, Northern Shoveler, Rosy Pelican, Gadwall, Wood Sandpiper, Spotted Sandpiper, Eurasian Wigeon, Black tailed Godwit, Spotted Redshank, Starling, Bluethroat and Long billed Pipit. In summer about 11 species of migratory birds such as Asian Koel, Black crowned Night Heron, Eurasian Golden Oriole, Comb duck, Blue cheeked Bee Eater, Blue tailed Bee Eater and Cuckoos come here</avifauna>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Sultanpur - Delhi - Agra - Fatehpur Sikri - Bharatpur - Agra - Bandhavgarh - Kanha - Jabalpur</travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airhead is Delhi (46 km)</air>
		<rail>The nearest railhead is Delhi (46 km)</rail>
		<road>There are buses and taxis from Delhi (46 km), Gurgaon (15 km) and neighboring centers</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Dachigam National Park</name>
		<place>Srinagar in Jammu &amp; Kashmir, Northern India</place>
		<major_attractions>Hangul (Kashmiri Stag), Musk Deer, Leopards, Himalayn Gray Langurs and Himalayan Weasel</major_attractions>
		<area>141 sq. Km</area>
		<ideal_time>Upper Dachigam : May - August,. Lower Dachigam : September - December. Dachigam National Park remains closed between January and April.Special permits are required to visit this part of India</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Vaishno Devi and Patnitop Hill Resort</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Srinagar(22km) and Jammu(200km)</major_accesses>
		<where>Dachigam National Park sets in unblemished bewitching scenic surrounds of the northern Indian state of Jammu and Kashmir. The national park is located at a distance of 22km from Srinagar. The park is enclosed by two ridges with a great variety of flora and fauna. The splendid forests of Dachigam are divided into two parts – Upper and Lower Dachigam</where>		
		<climate>The two parts of Dachigam National Park are located at varraying altitude of 1700m to 4300 m above the sea level. Winters can be dead chilly here while visiting park during the summer months can be enthralling. The maximum temperature here during the summer season reaches upto 14degree centigrade while in winters it is as low as 2 degree centigrade. Dachigam remains closed during the months between January and April</climate>
		<important_date>Dachigam has been declared as a protected area under Government of India since 1910. Previously, the park was auspices of king of Jammu and Kashmir. The inception of idea of such a park was to ensure clean drinking water for the City of Srinagar. But the whole aura of the place was such that it was decided to upgrade this park to a National Park. Dachigam national Park stands today as a treasure trove of some of the rarest species animals in India. Among them, the most prominent is Hangul or Kashmiri Stag</important_date>
		<flora>Coniferous forests cover a large area in Dachigam National Park. The mountainsides of the forest are thickly covered with wild trees. Running don the mountain's face are the alpine pastures, watrefalls, scrub vegetation with deep gullies and undulating meadows forms the flora here. You will find equisite variety of flowers which cover most of the terrain, except for the winters which are cold dry. One of the important lake of the region is Maskar Lake which flows out of Dagwan river. The wild tree variety here include: Wild Cherry, Pear, Plum, Peach, Apple, Apricot, Walnut, Chestnut, Oak, Willow, Poplar, Chinar, Birch, Pine and Elm.</flora>
		<fauna>Dachigam boasts of housing some of the rarest species of the world. Most eminent of all is Hangul or the Kashmiri Stag. Musk Deer, leopards, Himalayan Gray Langurs, Leopard Cats, Asiatic Black Bear, Jackals, Hill Fox, Himalayan Weasel, Yellow-throated Martens, Jungle Ctas, Long Tailed Marmots are the other important species that inhibit this place</fauna>
		<avifauna>With onset of every new season, the bird life of the park also changes. Among the major birds here, some of these are : Cinnamon Sparrows, Black Bulbuls, Himalayan Flycatcher, Lammergeier, Black and Yellow Grosbeaks and Himalayan Rubythroats</avifauna>
		<safari>Enjoy the picturesque forests and snow covered mountains along the vivid flora and fauna of this park. Since this park is located in scenic surroundings of Kashmir, it comes as a privilege to enjoy a mix of flora, fauna and natural beauty through jeep and elephant safaris at Dachigam. Jeep safaris are undertaken during the early morning hours till evening. A forest department guide is always their with the visitors on these jeep trips taken inside the park. Elephant safari trips are organized for tiger tracking early in the morning</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Sringar - Dachigam - Srinagar</travel-circuit>
		<air>Srinagar Airport is located at a distance of 22km and hence is a good access point</air>
		<rail>The nearest rail junction is Jammu at a distance of 200 kms away from Dachigam National Park</rail>
		<road>The Lower Dachigam region is accessible via a metaled road, but Higher Dachigam areas are accessible only on foot</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Hemis High Altitude National Park</name>
		<place>Ladakh, Jammu and Kashmir, Northern India</place>
		<major_attractions>Snow Leopards, Shapu, Bharal, Wild Sheeps and Goats</major_attractions>
		<area>3,350sq. Km</area>
		<ideal_time>For Mammal Viewing: September to March.	For Bird Viewing: March to May. From mid June to mis October, you can find a large number of trekking routes to its visitors.</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Leh, Ladakh</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Srinagar, Jammu and Chandigarh</major_accesses>
		<where>At an altitude ranging between 3,300 and 6,000 m above the sea level, Hemis High Altitude National Park is situated at Ladakh in Jammu and Kashmir. The park stretches from 33°15' to 34°20' North latitude and from 76°50' to 77°45'E longitude with an altitudinal range of 3,300 m at the confluence of the Indus and Zanskar rivers in the northwest to the 6,400 m Kang Yisay massif in the northeast. With rough terrain and abundant wildlife, this park attracts a large number of tourists annually. It is the largest high altitude and conserved national park of India. On the banks of Indus River, the park includes the cachements of Markha, Sumdah and Rumbak. The most prominent animal found here is Snow Leopard which has given this park, a status of Snow Leopard Capital of India. This treasure trove of scenic and unblemished beauty is located in northern region of India, at the foothills of HimalayaAt an altitude ranging between 3,300 and 6,000 m above the sea level, Hemis High Altitude National Park is situated at Ladakh in Jammu and Kashmir. The park stretches from 33°15' to 34°20' North latitude and from 76°50' to 77°45'E longitude with an altitudinal range of 3,300 m at the confluence of the Indus and Zanskar rivers in the northwest to the 6,400 m Kang Yisay massif in the northeast. With rough terrain and abundant wildlife, this park attracts a large number of tourists annually. It is the largest high altitude and conserved national park of India. On the banks of Indus River, the park includes the cachements of Markha, Sumdah and Rumbak. The most prominent animal found here is Snow Leopard which has given this park, a status of Snow Leopard Capital of India. This treasure trove of scenic and unblemished beauty is located in northern region of India, at the foothills of Himalaya</where>		
		<climate>The climate of area is one of extremes, with considerable daily and seasonal fluctuations. Precipitation is low with only 160.5 mm per year recorded at Leh. During winter the Zanskar River and its tributaries become frozen. Temperatures during winter drop typically to -15°C to -20°C at night and rise to near freezing point in daytime. Although summer temperatures can reach upto 30°C at the lower elevations, snowfall can occur at any time of year. Annual precipitation in Leh at 3,500 m in the Indus valley is about 10 cm, but rainfall and snow increase with altitude</climate>
		<important_date>This national park of India was established in 1981 to preserve the dwindling wildlife in Ladak. The park has been named after Hemis Gompa which is a believed to have been established in 1630 by Lama Tagstang Raspa and built by Palden Sara under the patronage of King Sengge. The Hemis monastic complex is located in the state of Jammu and Kashmir within the Ladakh region of the Western Himalayas, at an altitude of 12,000 feet making it one of the highest settlements of the world</important_date>
		<flora>You will find alpine and steppe trees predominantly at Hemis High National Park. These trees and shrubs are spread across the valley bottoms. Since the upper mountain slopes are moist, this area is characterized by alpine vegetation including: Anemone,Gentiana, Thallctrwn, Lloydia, Veronica, Delphinum, Care.x and Kobresia. The other parts of the park support steppe vegetation which is dominated by Caragana, Artemisia, Stachys, and Ephedra, present along the lower river courses</flora>
		<fauna>The park is famous for it's population of the rare Snow Leopards (Uncia uncia) and the Ibex (Capra ibex). Within the park, the best area for trying to spot the snow leopard is in the Shang valley area where it's density is the highest. Other than these two animals, the park also has Bharal (Pseudois nayaur), Wolf (Canis lupus), Pallas' cat (Felis manul), Tibetan argali (Ovis ammon hodgsoni), Blue sheep (Pseudois nayaur), Ladakh urial (Ovis vigne), Himalayan marmots (Marmota bobak), Tibetan Wild Ass or Kiang (Equus hemionus kiang), Wooly hare (Lepus oiostolus), wolves (Canis lupus), Dholes (Cuon alpinus), lynx (Lynx lynx), mouse hare or pika (Ochotona roylei) etc. To spot some of these animals, the best time is early morning and afternoons</fauna>
		<avifauna>There are about 70 varieties of birds that can be viewed here. Some of the common birds found here are: snow cock, chukor, magpie, Himalayan whistling thrush, white rumped shama, snow partridge, golden oriole etc. Other importants birds worth watching include: Great Grey Shrike, the Red Mantled Rose Finch, the Black Throated Thrush, the Robin Acceptor, the Spotted Flycatcher, various migrant Teal, the Red Flanked Blue Tail and the Great Nose Finch</avifauna>
		<safari>At such high altitudes, the best way to take a tour of some of the easy accessible areas is through jeeps. For higher altitudes, Jeep Safaris are not feasable and hence we recommend some enthralling trekking tours with trainned guides which will get you to some of the exciting spots within the park. These trekking tours will let you have a view of enslaving flora and fauna of the park. Take one such tour and wish that you also spot a growling leopard in the snow covered mountains</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Ladak-Mrakha Valley-Hemis High.	Delhi-Leh,Ladak-Rumbak Village-Hemis High National Park-Ganda La Pass</travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airport is Leh, which is connected by Indian Airlines to Delhi, Chandigarh, Srinagar, and Jammu</air>
		<rail>The nearest railhead is Jammu, situated at a distance of around 690 km. Jammu is connected to all parts of India</rail>
		<road>The Leh-Srinagar National Highway officially opens from May 15 to November 15 every year (depending on weather condition). The distances of some important destinations from Leh by road are: Srinagar, 434 km; Kargil, 230 km; Manali, 497 km; and Keylong, 380 km</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Eravikulam National Park</name>
		<place>Kerala, Southern India</place>
		<major_attractions>Nilgiri Tahr, Gaurs and Tigers</major_attractions>
		<area>97sq. km</area>
		<ideal_time>September to February are the best time to visit this park</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Chinnar Wildlife Sanctuary</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Coimbatore, Munnar</major_accesses>
		<where>Eravikulam National Park is situated at Rajamallay which sets on Munar-Udumalpet Road in the South Indian state of Kerala. The national park is situated at the higher altitudes of Western Ghats. Geographically, it is located at 9 deg. 40 min latitude and 77 deg. 20 min longitudes</where>		
		<climate>This region of Kerala is drenched with South West Monsoons. Although the park receives ample rainfall throughout the year, the months of June, July and August are the monsoon months. This is the time when this region receives maximum rainfall. The months of April and May are hottest here. From September to December, Eravikulam receives little rain with clear weather. Because of this, one can visit Eravikulam best in the months between September and February</climate>
		<important-date>Eravikulam-Rajamallay was declared a wildlife sanctuary in 1975. This sanctuary attained the status of a National Park within three years of its establishment in 1978. The main purpose of establishing this park was to protect and conserve Nilgiri Tahr. </important-date>
		<flora>The grasslands of Eravikulam are called “climax” grasslands, by the scientists. It so believed because of the fact that these grasslands have achieved ultimate state of splendor. The scenic beauty has evolved to a perfect state of harmony. Within these grasslands, there are patches sholas which means forest. One can find diverse variety of orchids and other flowers, adorning this place. These forests are blessed with leeches to linger the travellers. Even a maundering trip to these deep green forests can let one explore a lot</flora>
		<fauna>At Eravikulam you will find as many as 26 species of mammals. The most prominent of all are Nilgiri Tahr, Elephants, Langur, Marten, Small-clawes Otter, Tigers and Leopards. The grass lands on the hills can make you spot avid variety of wildlife here. Some of the endangered species of animals like Varai Aadu (hill goat) can also be spotted here. Eravikulam is endemic to Westren Ghats and is a abode for some of the red listed threatened mammals in India</fauna>
		<avifauna>Eravikulam has great flowering beauty which makes it a perfect dwelling ground for the birds. There are about 138 estimated number of birds that inhibit here. Some of the most popular birds that can be spotted here include: Nilgiru Wood Pegion, Kerala Laughing Thrush and White Bellied Shortwing. You can fine over a hundred species of butterflies and 19 species of amphibians. Twenty species of orchids and nine species of balsam can also be found here</avifauna>
		<safari>Eravikulam can be best visited on foot as you can make stoppages at regular intervals and explore the deep woods</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Munnar - Eravikulam - Periyar - Kumarakom - Kochi </travel-circuit>
		<air>Cochin is the nearest airport which is located at a distance of 135km from here. Private coaches and buses can be hired from Cochin to reach Eravikulam</air>
		<rail>Munnar is the nearest railhead town from Eravikulam, located at a distance of 13km from here. You can reach Eravikulam from Munnar by hiring a coach or a cab</rail>
		<road>Private coaches and cabs are available on hire to reach Eravikulam from different parts of Kerala</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Kumarakom National Park</name>
		<place>Kottayam, Kerala, South India</place>
		<major_attractions>Local birds like the waterfowl, cuckoo, owl, egret, heron and the water duck, as well as the migratory Siberian cranes. Parrots, teal, larks, flycatchers, wood beetle, and other birds are seen here during their respective migratory seasons</major_attractions>
		<area>101 acres</area>
		<ideal_time>Between June and August. You can watch migratory birds in the months between November and February</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Vembanad Lake </attractions>
		<major_accesses>Cochin</major_accesses>
		<where>Kumarakom Bird Sanctuary is located 12km from Kottayam in Kerela. Among the finest bird sanctuaries in India, Kumarakom is situated on the banks of Vembanand Lake. Well renowned for its avian population, Kumarakom offers a range of bird watching spots for avid bird watchers. Sprawling over a wide expanse of 101 acres, the enchanting wooded beauty of the sanctuary lures a large number of foreign visitors. Most interesting is the time when Siberian Cranes visit this sanctuary</where>		
		<climate>Kumarakom Bird Sanctuary enjoys tropical climate throughout the year. There is moderate temperature throughout the year. Cool and fresh breeze makes even warmest months bearable. Temperature is cool between November and March and is best time to watch migratory birds in a pleasant setting</climate>
		<flora>A large number of mangrove forests cover most of the area here. Green paddy fields and coconut grooves provide a perfect home to birds. The flora of this rugged terrain adds colors to this picturesque bird sanctuary</flora>
		<fauna>The sanctuary is a home to most of the avian species. Some of these permanently live and dwell here while there are other species of birds that migrate here from far off continents. Migratory birds which visit the sanctuary every year are Siberian Cranes, Indian Peafowl, Egrets, Darters, Herons, Parrots, Larks, Flycatchers, Wood Beetles and Teals. Resident bird species include Waterfowls, Cuckoos, Owls, Egrets, Herons and the water duck</fauna>
		<avifauna>Cochin - Munnar - Periyar - Alleppey - Kumarakom - Kochi. Bangalore - Nagarhole - BR Hills - Bandipur - Ooty - Munnar - Eravikulam - Periyar - Kumarakom - Kochi </avifauna>							<air>The Cochin International Airport is the nearest one, which is at a distance of 70 kms from the Muhamma boat jetty</air>
		<rail>The nearest Rail head is at Kottayam which is connected to all the major cities of India by several express trains</rail>
		<road>Kottayam is 14 km from Kumarakom and connected to rest of the country of India by both State Highways and National Highways. From here taxis and auto rickshaws are available for reaching the sanctuary</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Periyar National Park</name>
		<place>Kumily, Kerala, in the southern part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Elephants, Tiger, Nilgiri Tahr, Nilgiri Langur</major_attractions>
		<area>777 sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>From the months of October and June</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Alleppey, Cradomom Hills, Kumily, Boat Cruises.</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Kumily (4 km), Madurai (140 km), Cochin or Kochi (200 km), Kottayam (114 km), Ernakulam</major_accesses>
		<where>The Periyar National Park and Tiger Reserve is situated high in the ranges of the Western Ghats, in south Indian state of Kerala - known as the God’s Own Country. Periyar wildlife sanctuary in Kerala has a scenic lake at the heart of the sanctuary. Formed with the building of a dam in 1895, this reservoir runs around the contours of the wooded hills, providing water to the local wildlife through out the year. Though Periyar Kerala is a Tiger Reserve, tourists visit this place to view the Indian elephants in the act of sprinkling water and playfulness by the Periyar lake</where>		
		<important_date>The Periyar National Park was slated under the Project Tiger in the year 1972</important_date>
		<system>The physiology of the Periyar National Park mainly comprises of the western ghat hills in various shapes and sizes. These thickly wooded hills are dominated by water bodies, vast grasslands and even thicker forest areas. The densely forested valleys are abound in wild vegetation and animal life. Other than the river Periyar, the park and main lake located in the centre of the park are watered by two other rivers, the Azhutha and the Mullayar</system>
		<flora>Some of the deeper valleys contain tropical evergreen forest with extremely thick tree cover that even bright sunlight finds hard to penetrate. These trees that have grown to amazing heights of up to 130-140 feet seems to having being there forever. The few level areas in the park contains marshy grasslands near the edges of the lake and other water bodies. Spread out across the park are also patches of semi-evergreen forest used as important cover by many of the animal species </flora>
		<fauna>Apart from Elephants, the other animals to be seen in the Periyar sanctuary Kerala are Gaur, Wild Pigs, Sambar, Barking Deer, Mouse Deer, Dole or Indian Wild Dog and very rarely, a Tiger. There are, now, an estimated 40 tigers in the Periyar national Park. Four species of primates are found at Periyar - the rare lion-tailed macaque, the Nilgiri Langur, Gee's Golden Langur, Common Langur And Bonnet Macaque. Periyar also happens to be the habitat of the elusive Nilgiri Tahr, which is rarely to be seen</fauna>
		<avifauna>The birdlife comprises of Darters, Cormorants, Kingfishers, the great Malabar Hornbill and racket-tailed Drongoes</avifauna>
		<reptiles>The reptilian population boasts of Monitor Lizards that can be seen basking in the sun, on the rocks along the lakeshore. Visitors who trek into the Periyar national park often see a Python and sometimes even a King Cobra</reptiles>
		<boat_cruises>Boat cruises make the best option to check out the wilds of Periyar Sanctuary, as the Periyar lake presents an excellent boating spot for tourists today. Although it is uneasy to see many animals from the boats, still you come across a family of Elephants, Wild Boar, and Sambar Deer by the water's edge</boat_cruises>
		<travel-circuit>Cochin - Munnar - Periyar - Kumarakonam - Alleppey - Kovalam - Trivandrum.  Bangalore - Nagarhole - BR Hills - Bandipur - Ooty - Munnar - Eravikulam - Periyar - Kumarakom - Kochi </travel-circuit>
		<air>Kochi (Cochin) at 200 km or Madurai in Tamil Nadu at 140 km are the nearest airports from Periyar.</air>
		<rail>Kottayam at 114 km is the nearest railhead from Periyar</rail>
		<road>Kumily, the nearest town from Periyar is well served by both state and private buses from Kottayam, Ernakulam and Madurai in Tamil Nadu</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Thattekkad National Park</name>
		<place>Ernakulam, Kochi, Sothern India</place>
		<major_attractions>Malabar Grey Hornbill, Crimson-Throated Barbet, Bee-Eater</major_attractions>
		<area>128 sq km</area>
		<ideal_time>September - June</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Bolgatty Island, Willington Island</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Aluva (48km)</major_accesses>
		<where>Thattekad Bird Sanctuary is located at Latitude 76deg. 40'-76 deg.45'N and Longitude 10deg. 7'-11 deg. E. The bird sanctuary is located in Kothamangalam Taluk of Ernakulam district on the northern banks of the Periyar river. At the height of 35-523m above the sea level, this marvelous bird sanctuary is situated at Njayqapilli peak. 13 km north east of Kotyhamangalam, Thattekkad Bird Sanctuary is a home to some of the rarest species of birds in India</where>		
		<climate>Thattekkad Bird sanctuary experiences a tropical climate. The annual rainfall recorded here is round 3000mm. The weather remains pleasant throughout the year while monsoon hits this place in the months between May and July. It would not be recommendable to visit this park during monsoon as most of the area here becomes inaccessible</climate>
		<important_date>Thattekkad is Kerala's first officially recognised bird sanctuary. Established in 1983, the lush green sanctuary has more than 300 recorded species of forest and water birds. While many of them are resident birds, some are migratory. Important birds found here include large falcon, gray jungle fowl, white breasted water hen, hornbill, jungle bush-quail, etc. A study conducted by Bombay Natural History Society during 1985 identifies 253 species here</important_date>
		<flora>Thattekkad Bird Sanctuary Thatekkad Bird Sanctuary is located in the dense tropical evergreen and deciduous forests and grassland patches. The picturesque landscapes here makes it a choicest bird sanctuary for those who love being close to nature. Thattekkad also has extensive plantations of teak, rosewood, mahagony, etc. A variety of flowers and tress combine to form the bewitching fauna at this wildlife park</flora>
		<fauna>Thattekkad is famous for its exclusive bird life. Among the animals found here, elephant is an occasional visitor. Leopard, bear, porcupine, python and cobra can also be sighted here</fauna>
		<avifauna>Rare birds like the Crimson-Throated Barbet, Bee-eater, Sunbird, Shrike, Blackwinged Kite, Grey Heron and the Night Heron are also commonly sighted. Indian roller, cuckoo, common snipe, crow pheasant, jungle nightjar, kite, grey drongo, Malabar trogon, woodpeckeer, large pied wagtail, baya sparrow, grey jungle fowl, Indian hill myna, robin bird, jungle babbler and darter are some of the common birds found here.There are a few rare birds as well which include: sunbird, shrike, fairy blue-bird, grey-headed fishing eagle, blackwinged kite etc</avifauna>
		<bird_watching>Thettekkad is a popular bird watching destination. Take a ride over an elephant's back along elephant trainer to have a view of some of the rarest birds here. Jeeps are also available on hire</bird_watching>
		<travel-circuit>Kochi - Thattekkad - Munnar - Periyar </travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airport, is 71 kms from Thattekkad</air>
		<rail>The nearest railway station is Aluva, at a distance of 48 km. Kochi</rail>
		<road>The sanctuary is 13 kms North-East of Kothamangalam along the Pooyamkutti road</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Bandipur National Park</name>
		<place>Karnataka, in the southern part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Asian Elephants and Gaurs</major_attractions>
		<area>874.20-sq-kms</area>
		<ideal_time>Between the months of April and October</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Mysore &amp; Ooty (80-kms)</attractions>
		<major_accesses>The park is 220 km from Bangalore; 80 km from Mysore; 80 km from Ooty</major_accesses>
		<where>Bandipur National Park lies on the halfway down to the Mysore-Ooty highway. India's best-known wildlife reserves - Bandipur National Park is situated within Chamarajanagar district in the southern Indian state of Karnataka, and joins the south Indian states of Tamil Nadu and Kerala</where>		
		<climate>Blessed with a temperate climate and diverse geographical features, the park supports an outstanding variety of flora and fauna, making it an authentic paradise for wildlife</climate>
		<important_date>In 1973, Bandipur National Park In Karnataka became one of the first of India's Tiger Reserves and the southernmost of the nine reserves specially formed under Project Tiger. In 1974, intention was declared under the Wildlife Protection Act to notify the Bandipur Wildlife Sanctuary as a National Park</important_date>
		<flora>The scrubby jungles towards the eastern limits of the Bandipur National Park consist of stunted trees, intermixed with bushes and open grassy belts. Towards the northwestern fringes, there is a bit-by-bit shift in the vegetation, from open dry deciduous jungles to tropical mixed deciduous jungles. These diverse habitats of vegetation shelters an enormous diversity of animal life</flora>
		<fauna>With the arrival of pre-monsoon showers in April, Bandipur National Park begins to blossom in all its beauty. The native birds starts their breeding activities. The grasslands with sprouting grass are dominated by elephants and the majestic gaur. Bandipur is a paradise between April to October, for the tourist coming to watch the larger mammals in their natural habitats. During the summer season, when dryness exists over most parts of Bandipur, the backwaters of the Kabini Reservoir in the northwestern part of the park entertains huge gathering of large mammals, especially the elephant and the gaur. This rare character of Bandipur National Park makes a breathtaking view, and is almost the only one of its kind in Asia</fauna>
		<travel-circuit>Nagarhole - Bandipur - Mudumalai - B R Hills</travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airport is at Bangalore which is 220 km from Bandipur. Here you will find several means of road transport to reach the park</air>
		<rail>Mysore is nearest railhead, at a distance of 80-kms. Take a bus or taxi form here to reach the park</rail>
		<road>The park is 220 km from Bangalore; 80 km from Mysore; 80 km from Ooty. Well defined road is available between these cities and the park</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Nagarhole National Park</name>
		<place>Karnataka</place>
		<major_attractions>Elephant, King Cobra, Krait, Python, Monitor Lizard ,Toads, Tigers</major_attractions>
		<area>64,330 hectares</area>
		<ideal_time>October and April</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Madikere, Bandipur National Park, Madhumalli</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Mysore (80km)</major_accesses>
		<where>Sharing its boundaries with Bandipur National Park, Nagarhole National Park is situated 90km away from Mysore in Karnataka. Interestingly, these two sanctuaries for a part of Mudumalai Sanctuary in Tamil Nadu and Wayanad Reserve in Kerala. Nagarhole is a tiger's home and some of the rare wild species of India. This national park of India gets irrigated by the waters of Kabini river, which has a dam on it that separates Nagarhole from other sanctuaries in the surrounding area</where>		
		<climate>Summers here, are hot and dry with mercury level rising maximum to 33 degree centigrade. Summer months are best to spot tigers. It is the time when animals gather around lake and enable an exciting wild life viewing. The winters are cooler here but short spanned. From November to January are the winter seasons with temperature dipping to a minimum of 14 degree centigrade. This time is exceeding pleasant and best for those who do not wish to sweat much. From June to September are the rains which makes roads washed out and area swampy. We recommend not to visit this park during these months</climate>
		<important_date>Nagarhole was enunciated in 1955 as a game sanctuary. Realizing its importance in wildlife conservation, the area of the park was extended by combining Mysore forests with Nagarhole National Park. It was 1974, that this area took a shape of full fledged National Park. Apart from Kabini River, which drains most of the area here, there are other three rivers in the region including: Lakshmana, Teentha and Nagarhole. There are seasonal streams as well which merge into the four rivers here</important_date>
		<flora>The park has mostly deciduous terrain with a small area under dry tropical forests towards the east. Tectona Grandis and Dalbergia Latifolia trees are found in abundance in southern parts of the park. The eastern parts along Bandipur area and Sub mountain valley houses a large number of Wrightia Tinctoria and Acacia as part of dry forests here</flora>
		<fauna>Nagarhole National Park has sprightly wild life. Among the animals found here, most of the them are residents of Nilgiri Hills. Apart from Tigers, Niligiri Thar, Nilgiri Langur, bisons, leopards, asian elphants, wild boar, deer, dhole and porcupines are the major attractions of this park. Presence of grassy swamps is ideal for inhibiting snakes as well</fauna>
		<avifauna>There are a few canopy tress in the park that are as high as thirty meters and are hom eto some of the rarest species of birds in India like Malabar Trogan, Malabar Pied Hornbill and the Crested Hawk eagle. In all there are 250 variety of birds that are found here. Visit this park to explore the vivacious bird life</avifauna>
		<safari>For wild life explorers, there are innumerable options to move around the park. Jeeps can be rented to take a drive through the park. To have a more intricate view of the park, you can opt to go for an elephant ride. Hiking trails here can be very exciting but this excitement is restricted to a small area as you may become prey of a tiger with bright eyes, waiting for you behind the bushes. If you ask, the best way then jeeps are the obvious answer</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Bangalore - Mysore - Ranganathittu - Nagarhole - Bandipur - Mudumalai - Ooty - Cochin - Periyar - Varkala - Trivandrum </travel-circuit>
		<air>Nearest airport is located at Mysore, 80km away</air>
		<rail>Railhead closest to Nagarhole is Mysore which is 80 km away. Nanjangud is another railhead with a fewer trains to Nagarhole which is 55 km away</rail>
		<road>Buses connect Nagarhole to Bangalore (a ride of about 6 hours) and to a network of smaller towns across Karnataka, Tamilnadu and Kerala</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Bandhavgarh National Park</name>
		<place>Sahdol District, Madhya Pradesh, in the central part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Tigers, Leopards, Bears</major_attractions>
		<area>448 sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>Between the Mid-November to June. The park remains closed during the monsoon months from July to early November</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Kalchuri Archeological Remains, Bandhavgarh Fort (14th century fort)</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Khajuraho (via Satna) 230 km, Varanasi (via Rewa) 340 km, Katni 75 km, Rewa 115 km, Umaria 30 km, Kanha 250 km</major_accesses>
		<where>The Bandhavgarh National Park is located within the district of Sahdol in the central Indian state of Madhya Pradesh. The thick forest of Bandhavgarh National Park is nestled among the Vindhya hills</where>		
		<climate>The Bandhavgarh National Park provides its own climate, atmosphere, water and nutrition through its recycling systems. Bandhavgarh experiences climatic conditions that vary to opposite extremes. The temperature in the winters varies from 0 to 20 degrees centigrade between November and February.In the summers, the temperatures move to the other extreme and can go up to 46 degrees centigrade. Bandhavgarh has an average annual rainfall of 1200mm. The rains here give very little prior warning. The rains, however, bring good respite from the burning heat. The main monsoon season mostly begins only once the park is closed from June to November</climate>
		<important_date>The Bandhavgarh National Park was once a hunting ground of the royal family of Rewa. Bandhavgarh was declared a park in year 1968. In 1968, the Maharaja of Rewa handed over the area to the government for it's formation. At this time, the entire park covered an area of 106 sq-km, but now, it consists of an area of 448 sq-km. These much required extensions, to the northern and southern areas, of the park were done in 1982. These areas consisted primarily of Sal forests, which is the main tree-areas found in the entire park along with Bamboo. In the year 1993, the Bandhavgarh National Park was finally declared a tiger reserve under Project Tiger</important_date>
		<flora>Bandhavgarh has a large variety of tree cover. Bandhavgarh has an excellent tree and foliage concentration. About half the Bandhavgarh park is covered with fine trees of Sal, while mixed forests are found in the higher reaches of the hills. It is only in the slightly higher lands that it changes to a more mixed vegetation of sali, saj, saja, dhobin etc. Stretches of bamboo and grasslands extend to the north. The main wildlife viewing is still done in the core of the park with its 32 picturesque, wooded hills</flora>
		<fauna>The density of it's big cat population has made Bandhavgarh famous across the globe. Bandhavgarh is blessed with a large variety of natives in terms of animals. It is possible to sight tigers, leopards, gaur (Indian Bison-although some say this is no longer seen), chital (spotted deer), Sambar deer, Dholes, nilgais, wild boars, chinkaras, sloth bears, rhesus macaques, chital, black faced langurs, jungle cats, hyenas, porcupines, jackals, foxes, wild dogs, chausinghas and ratels, among others</fauna>
		<avifauna>Despite being famous for it's four legged inhabitants, Bandhavgarh National Park is also a bird lover's paradise. Keep a look out for white browed fantails, steppe eagles, green pigeons, white rumped shama, grey malabar hornbills, black and white malabar hornbills (quite a rare sighting), blossom headed parakeets, parakeets, blue bearded bee eaters, green bee eaters, white bellied drongos, owls, Jerdon's and gold fronted leaf birds, minivets, woodshrikes and the lovely paradise flycatchers</avifauna>
		<safari>One can enjoy exploring the wildlife in Bandhavgarh by two ways - Jeep Safari and Elephant Safari. Jeep safaris are undertaken during the early morning hours till evening. A forest department guide is always their with the visitors on these jeep trips taken inside the park. Elephant safari trips are organised for tiger tracking early in the morning</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Khajuraho - Bandhavgarh - Kanha - Nagpur </travel-circuit>
		<air>Khajurao at 230 km is the most convenient airport connected to the park by various domestic airline services with Agra, Delhi, Varanasi</air>
		<rail>The nearest railhead Umaria at 30 km is on the Katni-Bilaspur section of South-Eastern Railway. Another convenient railhead Satna (117 km) is on the Bombay-Howrah main line of the Central Railway</rail>
		<road>Bandhavgarh National Park is situated on the Satna-Umaria &amp; Rewa-Umaria highway. Madhya Pradesh State Transport Bus Services are also available from Rewa, Satna, Katni and Umaria</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Kanha National Park</name>
		<place>Mandal District, Madhya Pradesh, India</place>
		<major_attractions>Leopards, Tigers and Bears</major_attractions>
		<area>1,940sq. Km.</area>
		<ideal_time>February to June. The park remains closed from 1st July to 31st October. It can be closed earlier as well, depending upon the arrival of monsoon.</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Kanha Museum, Tadoba National Park (Maharashtra), Bamni Dadar(Sunset Point).</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Mandal</major_accesses>
		<where>At the height of 600-900 m above the sea level, Kanha National Park is situated in the central state of Madhya Pradesh in India. Tigers romancing in the scenic surrounds of the park is a much loved as well as inspiring thought for many. One of the world's best tiger reserve, Kanha is located among the Banjar and Halon valleys in Madhya Pradesh's Mandal/Balaghat districts.Over 1,940 sq km of bamboo thickets, extensive grasslands and dense sal forests make up Kanha- a series of plateaus which stretch across the eastern segment of the Satpura ranges in Madhya Pradesh. Out of this 940sq.km. Is core area</where>		
		<climate>Kanha National Park experiences tropical climate. The summers here are warm with mercury levels fluctuating between 40.6 degree centigrade to 23.9 degree centigrade. Summers here are hot and humid while winters are cool and pleasant. Temperature during winters ranges between 23.9 and 11.1 degree centigrade</climate>
		<important_date>The central Kanha valley was declared a sanctuary way back in 1933. The adoption of this sanctuary into a national park took place in 1955, after much turbulence and storm regarding rampant killing of wildlife in the area at the time. One of the famous success stories of the park is the survival of the Barasingha population in the park, which went down to as low as 66 animals in 1970 from the earlier 3000 and which through huge efforts have now revived to a respectable number of around 1000. With the help of Project Tiger, the population of tigers have doubled since 1976</important_date>
		<flora>The flora in Kanha National Park chiefly comprises of Southern tropical Moist Mixed Deciduous Forest and Southern Tropical dry Deciduous Mixed Forest types. There are huge plateaus in the park with vast grasslands. Since there were villagers who inhibited this place earlier, there are a number of meadows inside the park. River Sulkum, Banjar and Nila irriogate the topography at this park. The slopes of the plateaus here are thickly covered with Bija, Haldu, Dhaora trees which stand along the long stretches of Ban-rahar, Bamboo and Sindhur tress. If you love photography, the park offers some bewitching views which are worth a click</flora>
		<fauna>A major portion of the park is the core area with a wide variety of animal life. The major attraction of the ark is its tigers. Kanha is home to 22 species of large mammals. The major wildlife attractions in Kanha Wildlife Sanctuary are Royal Bengal Tigers, Leopards, Dholes (Indian wild dog), Indian Bisons, Sambar, Chital, Barasingha, Barking Deer, Black Buck, Chausingha, Nilgai, Monkeys, Mongoose, Mouse Deer, Sloth Bear, Jackal, Porcupine, Hyena, Jungle Cat, Hare, Rock Pythons among many others</fauna>
		<avifauna>Kanha National Park is a home to over 300 species of birds. The most commonly noticed birds in the park are Pea fowls, Storks, Pond Herons, Egrets, Indian Peafowl, Partridges, spotted Parakeets, Green Pigeons, Cuckoos, Drongos, Warblers, Kingfishers, Woodpeckers and fly catchers</avifauna>
		<safari>Elephant trainers at Kanha National Park can take you to an extensive trip to its expansive wildlife. Taking an elephant ride through the park can be joyous as you can easily spot vivid variety of birds as well. For wildlife enthusiasts, nothing would be as rewarding as this</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi-Mandla-Kanha National Park</travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest Airport to Kanha National Park is Nagpur (265 km), which is well connected by air to major cities of India</air>
		<rail>Jabalpur and Bilaspur are nearest Railway Stations</rail>
		<road>There is a daily bus service available for Kisli and Mukki from Jabalpur and back. Taxis are available for hire from Jabalpur, Bilaspur and Raipur. It is advisable to reach Kisli before sunset as vehicle are not permitted within the park after dark</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Pench National Park</name>
		<place>Seoni district of Southern Madhya Pradesh</place>
		<major_attractions>Tiger, large herds of Gaur (Indian Bison), 285 species of domestic and migratory birds</major_attractions>
		<area>757.89 sq. km</area>
		<ideal_time>Though the park is open from November to June, but the best time to visit the park is between March and June</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Pench National Park</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Khwasa, Nagpur</major_accesses>
		<where>Named after the Pench river, Pench National Park lies in the lower southern reaches of Satpura hills. Located on the southern boundary of Madhya Pradesh, Pench national park borders with states like Maharashtra. The park falls in the district Seoni (Madhya Pradesh), and is close to Nagpur (90 km)</where>		
		<important_date>Many of the locations of the park finding its description in popular book, the jungle book of Rudyard Kipling, gives the book origin setting. In 1977, the park was declared as sanctuary, which was declared as national park in 1983. In 1992, Govt. of India announced the national park as the 19th Tiger reserve of country. In 2002, the name of the national park was changed to Indira Priyadarshini Pench National Park</important_date>
		<climate>The national park of Pench has usually tropical climate, and is warm during the summer, and cold in winter. Winters, temperature ranging between 3º C to 16º C, are the most comfortable season to visit the park, but it doesn’t guarantee good wildlife viewing. summers (April- June), temperature soaring from 26º C to 42º C, are the best time to view rich wildlife in the park</climate>
		<flora>The mixed forest of the Pench National Park is origin to diverse floral species. Over 1200 species of plants have been recorded in the park, which make together a very suitable environ for hundreds of wild inhabitants to dwell in the park. The varied species of trees found commonly in the park are Moyan, Mahua, Mokha, Skiras, Tendu, Bija, Achar, Garari, Aonla, Ghont, Baranga, Amaltas, Kihamali, Khair, Palas. Bamboo trees are also pervaded in the park, but it is restricted to some valley</flora>
		<fauna>Pench National Park is famous for large herds of Indian Bison, Sambar, Nilgai, Cheetal, Wild Dog and Wild Pig. Predators roaming in the park are Tigers, Leopards, Wild Dogs and Wolfs. Other common animals that one can take sight in the park are Sloth Bear, Chousingha, Chinkara, Barking Deer, Jackal, Fox, Common Palm Civet, Small Indian Civet, Jungle Cat, Hyena, Porcupine and many others. approx 55 tigers, listed in the park, combine big fascination for wildlife tourists willing to spot tigers</fauna>
		<avifauna>The national park and tiger reserve of Pench is paradise, no less than Bharatpur National Park, for birders. Approx 285 species of birds including Malabar Pied Hornbill, Indian Pitta, Osprey, Grey-headed Fishing Eagle, Sarus Crane, White-eyed Buzzard, and many species of migratory birds invite nature lovers to explore them</avifauna>
		<travel-circuit>Panna - Khajuraho - Orchha - Gwalior </travel-circuit>
		<air>Nagpur is the nearest airport which has good air link with major air destinations like Mumbai and Delhi. From Nagpur, one can drive to Khawasa (80 km), from where Turia gate of the Pench national park is just 12 km</air>
		<rail>The nearest railhead from the national park is Nagpur (92 km), from where one can easily reach Khawasa in 2 hours drive, and can take another small drive to the Turia gate of the park (12 km from Khawasa)</rail>
		<road>From Nagpur (80 km) and Jabalpur (190 km), one can drive on National Highway 7, and can easily reach Khawasa, from where the park is just 12 km</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Panna National Park</name>
		<place>In Chattarpur District, Madhya Pradesh, in the central part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Deer, Chital, Crocodile</major_attractions>
		<area>543 sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>Between the Mid-November to June. The park remains closed during the monsoon months from July to early November</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Khajuraho Temple City (57 km)</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Khajuraho (57 km)</major_accesses>
		<where>The Panna Tiger Reserve is situated in the Vindhya Mountain Ranges and sprawls over Panna and Chattarpur districts in the north of the state. Panna National Park is the 22nd Tiger Reserve of India and 5th in the state of Madhya Pradesh in central India. The National Park holds the areas from the former Gangau Wildlife Sanctuary created in year 1975. The Gangau Sanctuary constitutes of territorial forests of the present North and South Panna Forest Division to which a portion of the adjoining Chhatarpur forest division was included later. The reserved forests of the Park in Panna district and some protected forests on Chhatarpur side were the hunting grounds of the former rulers of Panna, Chhatarpur and Bijawar princely states in the past. The reserve is located on either sides of the Ken river which rushes from south to north through the Lower Vindhyan Formations within the park</where>		
		<important_date>Panna National Park was created in year 1981 and was declared a Project Tiger Reserve by Government of India in year 1994</important_date>
		<fauna>The predominant species that inhabits the park is the deer, of which the most easily sighted are the graceful little Chinkara, the Indian gazelle, and the Chital. Other species that have their habitat in the park are Nilgai, Sambar, Chausingha or four-horned Antelope, Blackbuck, Sloth Bear, Leopard and the ubiquitous common Langur, Tiger, Leopard, striped Hyaena, Jackal, Jungle Cat, Chital, Nilgai, four-horned Antelope or Chowsingha, Wild Boar, Chinkara or mountain Gazelle, Gazella, crocodile and others</fauna>
		<avifauna>Panna National Park is equally rich in avifauna. The artificial lake, Chandpata, is the winter home of migratory Geese, Pochard, Pintail, Teal, Mallard, Red Wattled Lapwing, Large Pied Wagtail, Pond Heron, White - Breasted Kingfisher, Cormorant, Painted Stork, White Ibis, Laggar Falcon, Purple Sun bird, Paradise Flycatcher and Golden Oriole</avifauna>
		<travel-circuit>Panna - Khajurao - Orchha - Gwalior.  Agra - Gwalior - Khajuraho - Panna Tiger Reserve - Bandhavgarh National Park - Kanha National Park - Khajuraho</travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airport is at Khajuraho at a distance of around 57 km from the Panna National Park. There are daily domestic flights available to Delhi, Mumbai and Varanasi from Khajuraho</air>
		<rail>Satna, at a distance of around 90 km, is the nearest railway station. It is a major railway hub and is connected to many places in central and western India, the most important of them being Mumbai at a distance of 1,540 km</rail>
		<road>The park is well connected with the other parts of the region by a good network of roads. Distances of some important places in India from the Panna Tiger Reserve are Khajuraho 57 km, Bhopal 727 km, Delhi 889 km, Chennai 1,761 km, and Kolkatta 1,040 km</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Nandankanan National Park</name>
		<place>Chandaka Forest, 25-km from Bhuvneswar, Orissa, India</place>
		<major_attractions>White Tiger, Black Panthers and Gharial Crocodiles</major_attractions>
		<area>14 sq km</area>
		<ideal_time>October to March</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Madikere, Bandipur National Park, Madhumalli</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Bhuvneshwar (20km), Kolkata</major_accesses>
		<where>Better known as “Garden of Pleasure”; Nandankanan Zoo is situated 20km off Bhuvneshwar in Orissa. As part of Chandaka Forests here, the zoo is a perfect escape destination from hustle bustle of the city. The zoo lies on the lines of Kolkata-Chennai railway line and is very close to Barang Railway Station. With 362 hectares of forest area, Kanji Lake occupies a significant portion of 66 hectares. The first ever breeding ground of endangered species, Nandankanan Zoo boasts of the significant contribution that the park has made in wildlife conservation</where>		
		<climate>Summers are hot here with a maximum mercury level recorded being 40 degree centigrade. Winters are cooler and pleasant time to visit this park. The minimum temperature recorded during winters remains around 14 degree centigrade. With the onset of monsoons, the park experiences heavy rainfalls and makes most of its area inaccessible. You should try avoid visiting this park during monsoons as roads get washed out</climate>
		<important_date>This magnificent zoo in Orissa was established on 27December, 1960. The most important year in the history of this zoological park is 1980, when the regal white tiger received a new lease of life. Ganga and Deepak were the two tigers that were born to make this year much jubilated for all. At present there are about 34 tigers that are found here. In 1991, the tiger safari was established at this park in order to provide an enthralling view of the tigers from behind the protected bushes</important_date>
		<flora>Nandankanan is a home to various flourishing varieties of flora. The splendid environs of Chandaka forests and ripling waters of Kanjia Lake forms flora here. Giving it a gardening beauty are the flowers here. The zoo is thickly densed with trees like Bija, Sal, Asana and Anala</flora>
		<fauna>Nandankanan is world renowned for its white tigers. This internationally recognized zoo is home to a large number of animals which are on verge of extinction. Animals like Rhino, Manipuri Deer, Wild Ass, Tigers, Himalayan Black Bear, Lion Tailed Macaque, Chimpanzees, Orangutan, Hippopotamus, Zebra, Mouse deer, Blackbuck and Chousinga are most eminent. There are about 21 species of reptiles that can be found here</fauna>
		<avifauna>Nandankanan is a bird watcher's paradise. There are about 59 species of birds that are found at this park. Peafowl and White necked stork are the two birds that enslave wildlife enthusiasts with their bewitching beauty</avifauna>
		<safari>Lion Safari tours offered at this park enthrall the visitors at this park. Jeeps and elephants are also available on hire to have a ride through the park. Have a view of majestic wildlife of this park through its Safari tours</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Bangalore - Mysore - Ranganathittu - Nagarhole - Bandipur - Mudumalai - Ooty - Cochin - Periyar - Varkala - Trivandrum </travel-circuit>
		<air>Bhubaneswar Airport, 20km</air>
		<rail>Bhubaneswar is the nearest railway station from the zoo</rail>
		<road>Bhubaneswar is well connected to other parts of the state. Innumerable buses are available from Bhuvneshwar that enroute to Nandankanan</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Bharatpur National Park</name>
		<place>Bharatpur, Rajasthan, in the northwestern part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Sambar, Chital, Nilgai, Boar, Migratory Birds</major_attractions>
		<area>29 sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>Between the months of August-November for resident breeding birds and October- February for migrant birds</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Bharatpur Govenment Museum, Bharatpur Palace, Lohagarh Fort, Deeg Palace (32 km)</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Bharatpur is well connected by road from Agra (56 km), Delhi (176 km) and Jaipur (176 km), all of which have airport facilities too</major_accesses>
		<where>One of the finest bird sanctuaries in the world, Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary is a reserve that offers protection to faunal species as well. The Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary, also know as the Keoladeo Ghana National Park is a distance of 2 km form the Bhartapur town in Rajasthan India. The recent name Keoladeo, given to the Bharatpur Sanctuary is the name derived from an ancient Hindu temple, devoted to Lord Shiva, which stands at the centre of the park. The famous Bharatput Wildlife sanctuary is also known as the Ghana Wildlife Santuary. 'Ghana' means dense, referring to the thick forest, which used to cover the area. </where>		
		<alias_name>Keoladeo Wildlife Sanctuary, popularly known as Bharatpur Wildlife Sanctuary, is perhaps the only wildlife preserve, where the wildlife habitat has been created by a man - the Maharaja of Bharatpur. In earlier times, Bharatpur town used to be flooded regularly every monsoon. In year 1760, an earthen dam (Ajan Dam) was built, to save the town, from this yearly vagary of the nature. The cavity created by removal of soil for the dam was cleared and the Bharatpur Lake was formed.At the commencement of this century, the lake was developed, and was divided into several sections. A system of small dams, dykes, sluice gates, etc., was created to control water level in different parts. This became the hunting preserve of the Bharatpur royalty, and one of the best duck - shooting wetlands in the world. </alias_name>
		<important_date>Hunting was prohibited by mid-60s. The area was declared a national park on 10 March 1982, and accepted as a World Heritage Site in December 1985.</important_date>
		<flora>The Bharatpur Bird Santuary has a dense forest cover, which shelters a diverse flora. The vast flora is responsible in providing natural habitat to these migratory birds and also haven of free natural perpetuation. The diverse plant species found here are a real exception to the region. </flora>
		<fauna>The Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary is also inhabited by Sambar, Chital, Nilgai and Boar</fauna>
		<avifauna>More than 300 species of birds are found in this small wildlife park of 29 sq-km of which 11 sq-km are marshes and the rest is scrubland and grassland. The major attractions of tourists visiting the park are the numerous migratory birds, who come from places as far away as Siberia and Central Asia and spend their winters in Bharatpur, before returning to their breeding grounds. Migratory birds at Bharatpur bird sanctuary include, several species of Sarus Cranes, Pelicans, Geese, Grey Heron, Ducks, Eagles, Brown long eared bat, Hawks, Shanks, Stints, Garganey Teal, Wagtails, Warblers, Wheatears, Flycatchers, Buntings, Larks and Pipits, etc</avifauna>
		<birding_trips>Walking and cycling along the raised embankments offer an opportunity to get close to the rich bird life. A cycle rickshaw is another way of exploring the sanctuary. There are well-defined forest paths, which can easily be reached by foot or on a cycle or you can also hire a rickshaw that are available on hire. Rickshaw pullers have been trained by the park management in bird watching and are quite knowledgeable. Boats are also available on hire. A early morning boat trip or a late evening one is quite an enthralling experience to find out the hidden treasures of Bharatpur</birding_trips>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Bharatpur - National Chambal Sanctuary.     Delhi - Jaipur - Ranthambore - Bharatpur - Agra - Khajuraho - Bandhavgarh - Kanha - Nagpur </travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airport is situated at Agra, which is 56-kms from Bharatpur. </air>
		<rail>Regular rail services connect Bharatpur with all the major cities of India such as Delhi, Mumbai, Jaipur and Agra. The Bharatpur railway station is 6 km from the park.</rail>
		<road>An excellent network of roadway services links Bharatpur to all the major cities of the Rajasthan and its neighbouring states like Delhi, Uttar Pradesh, Haryana.</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Ranthambore National Park</name>
		<place>Near Sawai Madhopur, Rajasthan in the northwestern part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Tigers, Leopards, Boars</major_attractions>
		<area>392 sq-km.</area>
		<ideal_time>During the months of October - March and April to June.</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Ranthambore Fort (the 10th century fort) and Jogi Mahal in the park complex. Bakaula, Kachida Valley, Lakarda and Anantpura are also some place you can visit.</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Sawai Madhopur (11 km), Alwar, Jaipur (145 km). </major_accesses>
		<where>The Ranthambhore National Park in Rajasthan is situated in the eastern part of Rajasthan, where the Aravali Hill ranges and the Vindhyan plateau meet. The park falls under the district of Sawai Madhopur, which is also the nearest town located 11 km from the park.The Ranthambore National Park was once the hunting ground of the Maharajas of Jaipur. The rivers Chambal in the South and Banas in the North bound the Ranthambore National Park in Rajasthan India. Six man made lakes are the central focus of the Ranthambore park and many longlasting streams meanders through the entire park. The Ranthambore National Park has internal drainage and has no connection with any river system, even though two rivers bound the Park in it’s north and south side</where>		
		<climate>The park experiences drastic variations in climatic conditions. The temperature range is extreme with the mercury dipping to around 2 degrees centigrade in the winters and rising all the way up to 47 degrees centigrade in the summers.</climate>
		<important_date>The Ranthambore Tiger Reserve was declared a wildlife sanctuary in year 1957 and in year 1974 it gained the protection of "Project Tiger". It received it's status of a National Park in year 1981</important_date>
		<system>For the wildlife lovers, Ranthambore Wildlife Sanctuary Rajasthan offers an enthusiastic diversity of flora and fauna. The landscape fo the Ranthambore National Park is formed of massive rock formations, steep scarps, perennial lakes and streams and forest suddenly opening up into large areas of Savannah. The terrain of Ranthambore Wildlife Sanctuary fluctuates between impregnable forests and open bush land. Ranthambore National Park in Rajasthan is famous for its Tigers and is a delight treat for the photographers. For a relatively small area, the park has a rich diversity of fauna and flora - species list includes 300 trees, 50 aquatic plants, 272 birds, 12 reptiles including the Marsh Crocodile and amphibians and 30 mammals</system>
		<flora>The Ranthambore National Park Rajasthan is dotted with ancient Banyan Trees, Dhok and Pipal trees, clusters of mango trees and crisscrossed with evergreen patches. The forest is the typically dry deciduous type, with Dhok, being the most obvious tree found through out the region.Apart from Dhok, other species found here are - Am (Magnifera Indica), Imli (Tamarindicus indica), Babul (Accasia nilotica), Banyan (Ficus benghalensis), Ber (Zizyphus mauritania), Dhak or Chila (flame of the forest), Jamun (Syzygium cumini), Kadam (Authocephalus cadamba), Khajur (Phoenix sylvestris), Khair (Accacia catechu), Karel (Capparis decidua), Khejda (Prosopis specigera), Kakera (Flacourtia indica), Mohua (Madhuca indica), Neem (Azadirachta indica), etc</flora>
		<fauna>Tigers, the park's pride makes it one of the best places in the country to observe them. Apart from that a large numbers of Leopards, Striped Hyenas, Sambar deer, Chital, Nilgai, Common or Hanuman langurs, Macaques, Jackals, Jungle cats, Caracals, Sloth bears, Black Buck, Rufoustailed Hare, Indian Wild Boar, Chinkara, Common Palm Civets or Toddy cat, Coomon Yellow Bats, Desert Cats, Fivestriped Palm Squirels, Indian False Vampires, Indian Flying Foxes, Indian Foxes, Indian Gerbilles, Indian Mole Rats, Indian Porcupines, Longeared Hedgehogs, Ratels, Small Indian Mongoose, Small Indian Civets and Common mongoose are seen in the park</fauna>
		<avifauna>Ranthambore national park is also one of the richest reserves in bird species. Ranthambore, due to its varied terrain and abundance of water bodies, has an excellent population of birds, resident and migrant. There are about 272 different species of birds found in the Ranthambore National Park Rajasthan. The birds in the Park includes a large number of migratory birds. Some of the many varieties of birds seen here are the great Indian horned owl, various species of eagles such as Bonelli’s eagle and the crested serpent, spoonbills, partridge, quail, parakeets, Common kingfishers, owls and storks, geese and ducks. The most visible bird in Ranthambhore is the peacock, India's national bird</avifauna>
		<reptiles>Snub Nosed Marsh Crocodiles, Desert Monitor Lizards, Tortoise, Banded Kraits, Cobras, Common Kraits, Ganga Soft Shelled Turtles, Indian Pythons, North Indian Flap Shelled Turtles, Rat Snakes, Russel's Vipers, Saw-scaled Vipers and the Indian Chamaeleon.</reptiles>
		<fishes>Ranthambore due its numerous water bodies has a relatively large variety of fish to boast of. These species consist of : Bita (Labio Rohita), Catla (Catla catla), Greyei (Chhana matulion), Lanchi (Walago auto), Mahseer (Tor tor), Mirgal (Cirrchinus mrigala), Rohu (Labio rohita), Savank (Chhana punctatus), Seenghari (Mystus seenghala).</fishes>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Ranthambore - Bharatpur – Agra - Bandavgarh – Kanha - Nagpur – Mumbai </travel-circuit>
		<air>Jaipur at 145 km is the nearest airport from Ranthambore wildlife sanctuary.</air>
		<rail>Ranthambore National Park is around 11 km away from Sawai Madhopur railway station, that lies on the Delhi to Bombay trunk route</rail>
		<road>A good network of buses connect Sawai Madhopur, the nearest town from Ranthambore to all the major cities within the state of Rajasthan</road>
     </national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Sariska Wildlife Reserve</name>
		<place>37 km from Alwar, Rajasthan, in the northwestern part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Tigers, Leopards, Wild Dogs</major_attractions>
		<area>765.80 sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>Throughout the year, but the best period is during the months of October to June</ideal_time>
		<attractions>The Kankwari Fort (17th century fort), The Neelkanth temples (of the 6th-13th century AD), The Palace, The ruins of medieval temples of Garh-Rajor, (of 10th and 11th centuries AD)</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Alwar (37 km), Jaipur (110 km)</major_accesses>
		<where>The Sariska Wildlife Sanctuary in Rajasthan is situated only 200 km from Delhi and 107 km from Jaipur. Although larger than Ranthambore, it is less commercialised and has less tigers but a similar topography. The wide range of wildlife here is a wonderful example of ecological adoption and tolerance, for the climate here is variable as well as erratic</where>		
		<climate>The park bears a completely different look in the summer months and in the months post-monsoon. It looks extremely dry in the summers and becomes dense and lush green after the monsoons</climate>
		<important_date>The reserve was declared a wildlife sanctuary in 1958 and came under the "Project Tiger" as a tiger reserve in 1979</important_date>
		<landscape>Sharp cliffs of hills and narrow valleys of the Aravallis dominate the landscape of Sariska, whose forests are dry and deciduous. There aren't many good water bodies present within the park complex. There is a small lake to the left of the main road only a small distance from the entrance, which dries in the summers</landscape>
		<flora>There is some excellent grassland with water channels passing all over them. The forest area is mostly of the dry deciduous type with Dhok, Khair, Tendu, Ber, Surwal and Goria making up a majority of the vegetation</flora>
		<fauna>The Sariska National Park is home to several carnivores including Leopard, Wild Dog, Jungle Cat, Hyena, Jackal, and Tiger. These feed on an abundance of prey species such as Sambar, Chital, Nilgai, Chausingha, Wild Boar and Langur. Sariska is also well known for its large population of Rhesus Monkeys, which are found in large numbers around Talvriksh</fauna>
		<avifauna>The avian population in the park is also very healthy. During late summer and in the monsoon months, it is possible to find large numbers of peacocks in their dancing postures. Some of the bird species visible in the park are - Peafowl, Red Jungle Fowl, Spur Fowls, White Breasted Kingfishers, Golden Backed Woodpeckers, Great Indian Horned Owls, Quails, Partridges, Sangrouse, Tree Pies, Crested Serpent Eagles, Parakeets, Drongos, Sunbirds and Vultures</avifauna>
		<safari>The ideal way to explore the reserve is in your own vehicle. To go onto the jungle routes, you need to take an authorised guide. These guides can be booked at the reception of most of the hotels at the entrance, the park office and at the entrance. The other way that one can explore the remote areas of the jungle is by hiring a jeep from either the hotel or from the local jeep operators</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Sariska - Jaipur - Ranthambore - Bharatpur - Agra </travel-circuit>
		<air>aipur is the nearest airport from Sariska at a distance 107-kms.</air>
		<rail>The nearest railway station is at Alwar (37-kms)</rail>
		<road>Sariska wildlife sanctuary is situated off the Delhi-Alwar-Jaipur Road. Jaipur is located at a distance of 107-kms and Delhi at 200-kms from Sariska. Sariska is well connected with Alwar, which is further directly connected with bus services from Delhi and Jaipur.</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Mudumalai National Park</name>
		<place>Forest belt between the Western Ghats and the Nilgiri Mountains, in the extreme west of Tamil Nadu, Southern India</place>
		<major_attractions>Tigers, Sloth Bear, Spotted Deer and Leopards</major_attractions>
		<area>300 sq. km</area>
		<ideal_time>Mudumalai Wildlife Sanctuary can be visited from April-June and September-December</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Ooty (64km) and Coimbatore (160km)</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Coimbatore, Bangalore</major_accesses>
		<where>Mudumalai wildlife sanctuary sets in South Indian state of Tamil Nadu. Madhumalai means old hills ans interestingly sets amidst Bandipur and Annamalai sanctuaries. At an elevation of 1000m, it sprawls over an area of 321 sq. km. This wildlife sanctuary lies between Kerala and Karnataka. A mix of low hills, valleys and flat terrain sprinkled with a few swampy areas forms the terrain here. With largest elephant population of about 600, this is one of the famous wild life sanctuaries in Southern India</where>		
		<important_date>In 1940, Mudumalai was established as a wildlife sanctuary as an extension of Bandipur National Park. It was former erstwhile gaming reserve which was a famous hunting ground for Britishers who stayed at Ooty. The sanctuary saw an onslaught of gaurs during an epidemic that hit this area. There are few hunting sites within the park and government keeps a strong vigil on the activities taking place inside the Sanctuary.</important_date>
		<climate>Madurai experiences pleasant climate throughout the year. From October to March, the mercury level is recorded 20 degree centigrade and are winter months here. Summer months are from March to June when the temperature rises upto 30 deg. Centigrade. From July to September is a pleasant time with temperature being around 24 deg centigrade. Visiting Madhumalai during summer months can be a good time to spot tigers as they come at water pools within the sanctuary to fill their thirst.</climate>
		<flora>Madhumalai experiences tropical moist decidous vegetation towards western parts of the sanctuary. Dry-decidous and thorn scrub along the cast supports blaclbuck population. The flora at this park includes: Bamboos, Natural teak, Anogeissus latifolia, Terminalia, Crenulata/Terminalia Tomontosa, Grewia, and blooming trees like Indian Labumusum, Aredesia, Solanancea etc </flora>
		<fauna>There are two types of fauna found here: mammals and bird raptors. Among the mammalian population, Asian Elelphants, Barking deer, Musk deer, Gaur(Indian Bison), Sloth Bear, Giant Squirrel, Sanibar, Spotted Dear, Chowsingha, Indian Pangolin, Leopard, Wild Dog, Rusty Spotted Cat and Striped necked Mongoose are easily spotted animals. The bird raptors include: Changeable Hawk Eagle, Black Eagle, Oriental Honey-buzzard, Jerdon's Baza, Bonelli's Eagle, Crested Goshawk, Besra, Mottled Wood Owl, Brown Hawk Owl</fauna>
		<avifauna>You can spot diverse variety of birds at Mudumalai Wildlife Sanctuary. Grey Junglefowl, Red Spurfowl, Grey Francolin, Emerald Dove, Green Imperial Pigeon, Pompadour Green Pigeon, Grey-bellied Cuckoo, Indian Cuckoo, Alpine Swift, Black-hooded Oriole, Greater Racket-tailed Drongo, Black-headed Cuckooshrike, Painted Spurfowl, Painted Bush Quail, Whitebellied Woodpecker, Lesser Yellownape, Greater Flameback, Streak-throated Woodpecker, Chestnut-headed Bee-eater, Grey-headed Bulbul, Forest Wagtail, Crimson-backed Sunbird, Loten's Sunbird forms the avi fauna population here</avifauna>
		<safari>A safari tour to Mudhumalai Wildlife Sanctuary can be very interesting. The guides here know their animals by heart. Each lion, each elephant and each bison has its name assigned by these guides. Try insist your guide to have a deeper look into the wildlife and he will take you to some of the unbeaten paths in the sanctuary. You can sit on the elephant back and have an enthralling trip around the park</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Bangalore - Mysore - Ranganathittu - Nagarhole - Bandipur - Mudumalai - Ooty - Cochin - Periyar - Varkala - Trivandrum </travel-circuit>
		<air>Coimbatore is the nearest airport to access Mudumalai via air route. Private coaches or cabs can be hired from the taxi stand outside the airport to reach Madhumalai</air>
		<rail>Mettupalayam is the nearest broad gauge rail head, located 46km from Mudumalai</rail>
		<road>Accessing Mudumalai via road is not very difficult. Regular bus service from Bangalore, Mysore, Coimbatore, Calicut, Kanyakumari, Tanjavur, Tirupati, Cochin, Kotagiri, Udhagamandalam, Coonoor and Doddabeta is available which are destined to Madhumalai Wildlife Sanctuary</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Dudhwa National Park</name>
		<place>Kheri District of Uttar Pradesh, along Indo-Nepal Border</place>
		<major_attractions>Most eminent spot here is a Swamp Deer or Barasingha. Tigers and one horned Indian Rhinoceros are other important animals here</major_attractions>
		<area>About 811sq. Km. (core area of 648 sq km)</area>
		<ideal_time>February to April. The park remains closed from 15th June to 15th November</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Palia (10km.)</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Air-Lucknow (250 km) and a drive from Delhi (8 hours)</major_accesses>
		<where>With exceedingly diverse and cogent natural surroundings, Dudhwa National Park sets in Lakhimpur-Kheri district of Uttar Pradesh. Dudhwa is a tiger reserve park sprawling over an area of 614sq. km. The park is enclosed by Indo-Nepal border on its northern end while at the southern edge is River Suheli. One of the fines eco parks of India, Dudhwa houses a large number of endangered species including Tigers, Leopards, Swamp Deer, Hispid Hare, Bengal Florican etc.</where>		
		<climate>Dudhwa experiences extreme climates. Summers are sweating hot. Temperature during summers rise upto 40 degree centigrade. Winters are chilly with temperature ranging between 20 degree to 30 degree centigrade. The average annual rainfall recorded ranges around 16cm. For there are two extreme climates observed here, we recommend tourists bring their clothes accordingly. For summers, light cottons can be easily worn but for winters, you must bring light woolens in colors that do not scares animals</climate>		
		<important_date>Earlier known as Sonaripur Sanctuary, there was marked decline recorded in number of Barasingha population. In 1958, for the conservation of this rare species, this wilderness sanctuary was upgraded to be named as Dudhwa Sanctuary. In 1977, the area of the park was further increased and it was renamed as Dudhwa National Park. After eleven years of its upgradation, Dudhwa became one of the centers of Project Tiger wherein, the area of Kishanpur Sanctuary was also added to this National Park to create Dudhwa Tiger Reserve</important_date>
		<flora>On the foothills of Himalayas, Dudhwa National Park has extensive stretches of thick sal forests, grasslands and wet marshes. All stand in a perfect setting that best harbors a wide range of flora here. The reminiscent forests of the park cover a wide area with termite mounds and patches of reverie trees, forming the flora at this National Park</flora>
		<fauna>Notable variety of rarest species of fauna can be found at Dudhwa National Park. The fascinating wildlife here includes, sloth bear, ratel, civet, jackal, leopard cat, fishing cat, jungle cat, spotted deer, hog deer and barking deer. Most interesting and rarest spot among all the animals here is Hispid Hare which is a dark brown animal with bristly fur and was believed to have extinct but rediscovered in 1984. This animal is of great interest for wildlife conservationist. Another important animal here is one horned Indian Rhinoceros. It is one of the conserved animals in the park</fauna>
		<avifauna>Dudhwa is a paradise for bird lovers as it offers more than 400 species of birds. Since the park is situated on the foothills of Himalayas, surrounded by a large number of swampy grounds and lakes, it is a cool resting place for migratory birds. If you are a keen bird watcher, we can recommend Banke tal here where you can easily spot vivid birds of the park. Some of the important birds here include: egrets, cormorants, grey heron, ducks, geese and teal. You can also visit Dudhwa for an extraordinary variety of owls: great Indian horned owl, the brown fish owl, the dusky horned owl, scoops owl, jungle owlet, the brown wood owl and tawny fish owl. Colorful birds - varieties of woodpeckers, barbets, minivets, bulbuls, common kingfishers, bee eaters, orioles, drongos and hornbills are all part of its rich bird life</avifauna>
		<safari>Riding through the park with elephant trainers can be great fun. Since most of the area has marshy swamps, the most convenient way to move around the park is a ride on elephants back. With a nominal charge, you can move around the park in complete natural way. Jeeps are also available to cut through tedious and slow elephant rides</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi-Lucknow-Kishanpur-Dudhwa</travel-circuit>
		<air>Lucknow, Dhangarhi (Nepal, 35 km.) are the nearest Airports</air>
		<rail>Dudhwa (4 km.), Palia (10 km.), Mailani (37 km.) are the railway stations located adjoinin to this place</rail>
		<road>Drive from Delhi (8-9 hours) or take the train to Shahjehanpur and drive to Dudhwa (3 hours). Alternatively fly to Lucknow and drive to Dudhwa (245 km, 6 hours).</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Corbett National Park</name>
		<place>Uttaranchal, in the northern part of India</place>
		<major_attractions>Tigers, Leopards, Crocodiles</major_attractions>
		<area>1,200 sq-km.</area>
		<ideal_time>From November 15 to June 15. Corbett remains closed between June 16 and November 14, during the monsoons</ideal_time>
		<attractions>Ramnagar (fishing base camp), Lohachaur (15 km) - good place for anglers, </attractions>
		<major_accesses>Dhikala is about 300 km from Delhi, 145 km from Lucknow and 51 km from Ramnagar.</major_accesses>
		<where>The Corbett National Park is located in the foothills of the majestic Himalayas in the state of Uttranchal in India. The Corbett National Park is home to a variety of flora and fauna. It is famous for its wild population of Tigers, Leopards and Elephants. Once a popular hunting ground of the British, the Corbett National Park was named in honour of the late Jim Corbett, the legendary hunter-naturalist turned author and photographer, who spent most of his years in this area and contributed in setting up the park. </where>		
		<climate>Temperature in winter's can go down to 4 degrees centigrade at night and the entire jungle is extremely dry in the summer months as the temperatures reach as high as 44 degrees centigrade. Rainfall: 1400mm-2800mm</climate>
		<important_date>Corbett National Park was established in 1936, as the Hailey National Park. With the help of the World Wildlife Fund, Project Tiger was launched in Corbett National Park in 1973 and this park was one of the first such tiger reserves in the country.</important_date>
		<system>India's first national park and the first sanctuary to come under Project Tiger, Corbett National Park exhibits a variety of vegetation making it the ideal habitat for the Tiger and its prey. The varied topography comprises hilly and riverine areas, temporary marshy depressions, plateaus and ravines. In the Jim Corbett National Park are found 110 tree species, 50 mammals species, 580 bird species and 25 reptile species</system>
		<flora>A majority of the vegetation in Corbett consists of Sal trees (Shorea robusta), mainly in the lower regions. The higher regions have a larger variety of plants and trees. Some of these are the Chir (Pinus roxburghii), anauri (Legestroemia paruiflora) and Bakli (Anogeissus latifolia). Also found in various parts of the park are many different varieties of bamboo. One plant, (actually a weed) which is a major irritant to the park authorities and is widespread in the jungle is the Lantana.</flora>
		<fauna>Corbett is a haven for Tigers as well as its prey, which include four kinds of Deer, Wild Boar and some lesser-known animals. Apart from Tigers, Elephants, Leopards / Panthers, Jungle cats, Royal Bengal Tigers, Fishing Cats, Leopard cats, Himalayan black bears, Sloth bears, Jackals, Martens, Dholes, Civets, Mongooses, Otters, Hares, Porcupines, Chital (spotted deer), Sambar deer, Hog deer, Barking deer, Ghorals, Wild Boars, Pangolins, Macaques, Langurs and Blue Bulls (Nilgais) are some of the species which are found here</fauna>
		<avifauna>Herons, Darters, Cormorants, Lapwings, Paradise Flycatchers, Munias, Weaver birds, Fishing eagles, Serpent eagles, Spotted Eagles, Black throated Payas, Mynas, Indian Roller, Jungle Fowl, Vultures, Thrushes, Barbets, Peacocks, peahens, Kingfishers, migrant Gulls, Moorhens, Ducks, Geese, Sandpipers, Nightjars, Cuckoos, Woodpeckers, Wagtails, Black winged Kits, Drongos, Doves, Plovers, Black necked Storks, Parakeets, Sarus Crane, Owls, Chir Pheasants, Kalij Pheasants, Grebes, Grey Lags, Snipes, Harriers, Ospreys, Minivets, Babblers, Hornbills, falcons and Stone Curlews. Corbett has nearly 600 bird species officially recorded in it’s log books</avifauna>
		<fishes>Goonch, Mahaseer, Trout and many other smaller species are found here. </fishes>
		<reptiles>Gharials (fish eating Crocodiles), Mugger Crocodiles, Monitor Lizards, turtles, Cobras, Pythons and the Sal forest Tortoise</reptiles>
		<safari>The Jim Corbett National Park endorses Jeep Safari, Horse Safari, Bird Safari, Elephant Safari, Fishing safari and the Nature walk. Take an early dawn elephant back safari with an authorized mahout guide. Jeeps Safari, is the most convenient and comfortable way to travel within Corbett National Park. Jeep rides can be arranged at the Tourist Centre. Although jeeps penetrate deeper into the forest than elephants, they cannot get nearly as close to the wild animals. The jeeps can be rented for the park trips from Ramnagar, from the KMVN Tourist Lodge and other travel agencies</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Agra - Jaipur -Pangot (Nainital) - Corbett National Park - Rishikesh </travel-circuit>
		<air>Phoolbagh, Pantnagar at a distance of 50 km is the nearest airport. Delhi at a distance of 300 km is the nearest international airport</air>
		<rail>Ramnagar is on the broad gauge track from where the road transport options have to be availed to reach the park. For faster trains and connections to other parts of India change at Moradabad</rail>
		<road>Dhikala is 300 km from Delhi, 145 km from Lucknow and 51 km from Ramnagar. Ramnagar is served by frequent buses to and from Nainital and Ranikhet, 112 km north. Buses arrive every half hour or so after the eight hour trip from Delhi; Delhi Transport corporation also runs semi deluxe services</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Rajaji National Park</name>
		<place>Foothills of Shivalik Ranges in Himalayas foothills</place>
		<major_attractions>Elephants, deers, Laopards and Ghorals</major_attractions>
		<area>820.42 sq km</area>
		<ideal_time>From December to March. Beyond April, it is extremely hot here. </ideal_time>
		<attractions>Haridwar(9km), Rishikesh(6km)</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Kotdwar(25), Dehradun(25km)</major_accesses>
		<where>Rajaji National Park is situated along the hills and foothills of Shivalik ranges in the Himalayan foothills and represents the Shivalik eco-system. On the map it is located between Haridwar (Latitude 290 56’ 40”) and Dehradun (Latitude 300 20’ North) and 790 80’ E Longitude (Dehradun 780 01’ 15” E (Ramgarh), Chillawali- 770 54’ 30” East).</where>		
		<climate>The three main seasons in the Himalayan foothills are: winter, summer and monsoons. The best time for a safari or a bird watching trip is during winter (November to February) when the days are pleasant (20-25 degree Centigrade), nights cold and humidity is low. Temperature rises rapidly to 40-48 degree Centigrade in the hot season (March to June) and rainfall increases with the occasional thunderstorm. Humidity is high in the rainy season (July to October), with over 750 mm of precipitation in July to August, and there is little temperature variation. Annual rainfall ranges from 1200-1500 mm</climate>
		<important_date>With a wide expanse over 820sq km, Rajaji National Park is an amalgamated form of three wildlife sanctuaries: Rajaji, Motichur and Chilla. All these sanctuaries with different vegetation zones and wild life were combined together in 1983 to form a National Park. A combined form of these distinvt wildlife sanctuaries came to known as Rajaji National Park</important_date>
		<flora>Broadleaved deciduous forests, riverine vegetation, grasslands and pine forests form the range of flora at these parks. The dense jungles here are home to vivacious wildlife here. The varied topography of the national park is also responsible for vivid animal life inhibited here. The under-wood is light and often absent, consisting of Rohini (Liollotus philippinensis), Amaltas (Cassia Fistula), Sandan (Ougeinia Oojeinensis), Pipal (Bauhienia Lazan), Mahal (Pyrus Pashla), Chamaror, (Ehretia Laevis), Aonia (Emblica Officinalis), Kachnar (Bauhienia Variegata), Ber (Ziziphus Mauritiana), Chilla (Casearia tomentosa), Bel (Aegle Marmelos), etc</flora>
		<fauna>Endowing a wide variety of fauns in its lap, Rajaji National park has a lot to offer to wildlife eccentrics. With pristine scenic beauty and rich bio-diversity, Rajaji is a much reckoned park of India. There are about 23 species of mammals that inhibit this park. Indian elephants, spotted dear, sambhar deer, barking deer, blue bull, hog dear, wild boar, Jungle cat, Rhesus monkey and Lepidoptera are the mammals found here</fauna>
		<avifauna>There are about 315 species of birds that inhibit this park. India's National bird, Peacock is found here in abundance. Innumerable variety off butterflies and small birds add to the beauty of this place. Rusty cheaked Scimitar, Babbler, Golden-spected Warbler, Chestnut-tailed Starling, Brown Hawk-Owl, Drongo Cuckoo, Great Hornbill are only a few names of birds that are found here</avifauna>
		<safari>Its important to take permissions from the forest department before entering the premises of park. The park can be best viewed on an Elephant safari. Alternatively one can also take Jeep safari to see the park</safari>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Haridwar - Rajaji National Park - Rishikesh</travel-circuit>
		<air>Nearest airport is Jolly Grant, Dehradun, 33km.</air>
		<rail>Nearest railhead is at Haridwar ( 8km.) and Dehradun (24km).</rail>
		<road>The National Park is 220 kms. from Delhi and from Lucknow it is at a distance of 510km.</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Valley Of Flowers</name>	
		<location>On the upper expansions of Bhyundar Ganga in the state of Uttranchal in the northern part of India.</location>
		<time_to_visit>From mid July to mid of August. The valley can be visited only during the day and overnight stay is prohibited</time_to_visit>
		<weather>Salubrious and Pleasant.</weather>
		<known_for>The Rich Biological Resource</known_for>
		<general_info>Discovered by Frank S. Smith, an English mountaineer explorer and Botanist, while on an expedition to Mt. Kamet, the Valley of Flowers is a Nature's Gift to Man. The Valley of Flowers in the north Indian state of Uttranchal is a booming bouquet of beautiful, lively and multihued flowers. The Valley of Flowers National Park, spanning over an area of 87.5 sq km has the largest potpourri of wild flower species. Known to the inhabitants as the Bhyundar valley, the Valley of Flowers is hidden from the scrutinizing eyes of the civilization. The valley was declared a National Park in year 1982. The Valley of Flowers is also associate with the legendary story, which says that this the area from where Hanumanji of Ramayana collected 'Sanjeevani' herb to revive Lakshman. The Valley of Flowers National Park starts from Ghangharia but the main valley starts after crossing the gorge and the stream originating from Nar Parvat, 3 km from Ghangharia. In front of the Valley stands the snow capped peak of Ratban Parvat and at the background is the Kunt Khal. Towards the left is Nar Parvat, which bisects the Badrinath valley from this valley, and to the right is thick Birch forest on the hill sides. Below the forest is the meadow. River Pushpavati flows through the valley and there are many waterfalls enhancing the beauty of the valley. The splendour and the dazzling beauty of the valley beckons tourists from all the corners of the world. </general_info>
		<wildlife_resource>Almost 300 species of wild flowers bloom here in natural way. The bloom starts immediately after the melting of snow but the peak blooming period is from mid July to mid of August. The abundant natural resource of the valley captivates a large number of nature lovers, environmentalists and tourists every year. The wild flowers like the Himalayan blue poppy, daisy, dianthus, calendula, white and yellow anemones bloom and swing with life during the monsoons. Some other species are Anemone, Geranium, Marsh marigold, Prinula, Potentilla, Geum, Asters, Lilium, Ranunculus, Corydalis, Inula, Braham kamal, Campanula, Pedicularis, Arisaema, Morina, Impatiens, Bistorta, Ligularia, Anaphalis, Saxifrages, Sibbaldia, Thermopsis, Trollius, Codonopsis, Dactylorhiza, Cypripedium, Strawberry, Epilobium, Rhododendrons and numerous others. Most of the flowers have medicinal values too. The abundance of Asmanda fern in this valley is a rare sight than in other Himalayan valleys. The valley remains in bloom for three months while the floral arrangement keeps on changing every few days. By September the hue of the Valley starts changing and autumn bids farewell to flowers and the entire vegetation remains resting continuously for next five months when the valley is snow wrapped.Apart from the flowers some species of Butterfly, Musk deer, Blue sheep (Bharal), Himalayan bear, Himalayan Tahr, Himalayan mouse hare and some Himalayan birds and Snow leopard are also found in this area. To conserve the nature’s beneficient gift and to maintain the natural balance of the valley.</wildlife_resource>
		<air>The nearest airport is Jolly Grant, Dehradun, 319 km</air>
		<rail>The nearest railhead is at Rishikesh, 302 km</rail>
		<road>Off the Rishikesh-Badrinath road, 17 km from Govindghat. (25 km from Badrinath). From Govindghat the distance has to be trekked. Bus services are available to Govindghat. Porters are available at Govindghat and Ghangharia</road>
	</national_park>
	<national_park>
		<name>Sunderbans National Park</name>
		<place>Piyali (72 km from Kolkata by road), West Bengal, in the eastern part of India.</place>
		<major_attractions>Royal Bengal Tiger, Ridley Sea Turtle</major_attractions>
		<area>1330.10 sq-km</area>
		<ideal_time>During the months of September and May. Winter is the time to see the Royal Bengal Tiger sun-bathing on the river banks</ideal_time>
		<attractions>The Sajnakhali Sanctuary (famous for its rich avian population), Netidhopani (ruins of a 400 year old temple), Bhagabatpur, Kanak, Haliday Island, Piyali, Kaikhali Island</attractions>
		<major_accesses>Gosaba (50-kms), Kolkata</major_accesses>
		<where>The Sundarbans National Park lies in the south-east of Kolkata in the 24-Paraganas District of West Bengal and forms part of the Gangetic Delta, which borders on the Bay of Bengal. The vast swampy delta of the two great Indian rivers, Brahamaputra and the Ganges stretches over areas consisting of mangrove forests, swamps and forest island all knotted in a network of small rivers and streams. The Sundarbans National Park in West Bengal is home of the Royal Bengal Tiger and is also the largest mangrove forest in the world, forming the core of this region. The Sundarban region has derived its name from the Sundari trees, once found in large number here.The Ganges and the Brahmaputra form this alluvial archipelago of 54 islands watered by the Bay of Bengal. The islands Goasaba, Sandeshkali and Basanti form the northern boundary of the Sundarbans; on the south is the sea; to the west side of the Sunderbans park is the Matla and Bidya Rivers and to the east is the international boundary of Bangladesh.</where>		
		<climate>Rainfall is heavy and humidity high (80% on average) due to the proximity of the Bay of Bengal. The monsoon usually lasts from mid-June until mid-September, after which fair weather prevails until mid-March. Mean annual maximum and minimum temperatures recorded are 34°C and 20°C, respectively. Prevailing wind is from the north and north-east from October to mid-March, although January and February are quieter months. Violent south-westerlies prevail from mid-March to September. Storms are common in May and October-November, sometimes developing into cyclones which are usually accompanied by tidal waves and cause much loss of life and damage to property and the forests .</climate>
		<important_date>The Sundarbans National Park was established as a national park on 4 May 1984. Before this it was been declared as a wildlife sanctuary in the year 1977. It was been designated as the core area of Sundarbans Tiger Reserve in December 1973. Sunderbans National Park was inscribed on the World Heritage List in year 1985. </important_date>
		<landscape>The area that makes up the Sunderban National Park is the largest estuarine mangrove forest in the world. With the altitude averaging at 7.5 m above sea level, there is hardly any highland variation throughout the park at the Sundarbans. The park is dotted with 54 small islands that are networked by many tributaries of the mighty rivers Ganga and Brahmaputra, which finally flow out at the southern tip into the Bay of Bengal</landscape>
		<flora>The main forest cover in the Sunderbans comprises of estuarine mangrove forests intermixed by swamp and littoral forests. There is mangrove scrub forest, salt water mixed forest, brackish water mixed forest and alluvial grasslands. Due to the dense and huge forest reserve, Sundarbans has also been classified as a World Biosphere Reserve. Some of the more commonly found plants and trees in the park are Genwa, Dhundal, Passur, Garjan, Kankra and Goran</flora>
		<fauna>The Sundarbans forest is home to more than 400 tigers. The Royal Bengal Tigers have adapted themselves very well to the saline and aqua surroundings and are extremely good swimmers.The animal number of the Sundarbans is quite varied keeping it's climatic conditions in mind. Apart from the Royal Bengal Tiger, Sundarbans houses - Fishing Cats, Macaques, Wild Boar, Common Grey Mongoose, Fox, Jungle Cat, Flying Fox, Indian Pangolin, Chitals, etc</fauna>
		<avifauna>Due to climatic conditions popular at the park, it creates an ideal habitat for the native as well as migratory birds of a numerous variety. Some of the more popular birds found in this region are - Open Billed Storks, White Ibis, Water Hens, Coots, Pheasant Tailed Jacanas, Pariah Kites, Brahminy Kites, Marsh Harriers, Swamp Partridges, Red Jungle Fowls, Spotted Doves, Common Mynahs, Jungle Crows, Jungle Babblers, Cotton Teals, Herring Gulls, Caspian Terns, Gray Herons, Brahminy Ducks, Spotted Billed Pelicans, Large Egrets, Night Herons, Common Snipes, Wood Sandpipers, Green Pigeons, Rose Ringed Parakeets, Paradise Flycatchers, Cormorants, Fishing Eagles, White Bellied Sea Eagles, Seaguls, Common Kingfishers, Peregrine falcons, Woodpeckers, Whimprels, Black-Tailed Godwits, Little Stints, Eastern Knots, Curlews, Golden Plovers, Pintails, White Eyed Pochards and Whistling Teals</avifauna>
		<aquafauna>Some of the fish and amphibians found in the parks are Saw Fish, Butter Fish, Electric Rays, Silver Carp, Star Fish, Common Carp, Crabs, Prawn, Shrimps, gangetic Dolphins, Skipping Frogs, Common Toads and Tree Frogs. </aquafauna>
		<reptiles>The Sundarbans National Park has an excellent number of reptiles that are seen within its area. Some of the most seen are - Olive Ridley Turtles, Sea Snakes, Dog Faced Water Snakes, Green Turtles, Estuarine Crocodiles, Chameleons, King Cobras, Salvator Lizards, Hard Shelled Batgun Terrapins, Russels Vipers, Mouse Ghekos, Monitor Lizards, Curviers, Hawks Bill Turtles, Pythons, Common Kraits, Chequered Killbacks and rat Snakes</reptiles>
		<boat_cruise>The best and only means of travelling the park is to hire a boat and float down the various lanes formed by the many flowing rivers. Either hire one, which is operated by the locals in the area or one of the two luxury launches - M.V. Chitrarekha and M.V. Madhukar, operated by the tourism department. The M.V. Chitrarekha offers all the basic facilities required by the tourists, including overnight accommodation. The local boats are available at Canning, Gosaba and Basanti whereas the luxury launches starts their journey only from Canning.</boat_cruise>
		<travel-circuit>Delhi - Guwahati - Kaziranga National Park - Guwahati - Bagdogra - Kalimpong - Siliguri - Kolkata - Sunderbans National Park</travel-circuit>
		<air>The nearest airport is Kolkata, at 112 km</air>
		<rail>Canning is nearest railhead, at a distance of 48 km</rail>
		<road>Road transportation is available from Kolkata for Namkhana (105-kms), Sonakhali (100-kms), Raidighi (76-kms), Canning (64-kms), and Najat (92-kms), which are all near the Sunderbans and have access to the riverine waterways</road>
		<water>Sundarbans are approachable only by riverrine waterways. Motor launch facilitiy are available from Namkhana - Bhagabatpur Crocodile Project- Sagar Island -Jambudwip; from Sajnekhali - Sudhanyakhali-Buridabri- Netidhopan-Holiday Island; from Sonakhali - Gosaba; from Raidighi - Kalas.</water>
	</national_park>
</national_parks>